<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trumpet in Sion, sounding a general alarm in the nation. By J.G.G.</title>
            <author>Gailhard, J. (Jean).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 242 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85880</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G42A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232835</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47683454</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47683454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85880)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2655:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trumpet in Sion, sounding a general alarm in the nation. By J.G.G.</title>
                  <author>Gailhard, J. (Jean).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 115, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed: and are to be sold by Dan. Browne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [4]</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded and tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Christ Church (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apocalyptic literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:2"/>
            <p>THE TRUMPET IN SION, SOUNDING A General Alarm IN THE NATION. <hi>By</hi> J. G. G.</p>
            <q>Blow the Trumpet in <hi>Zion,</hi> and ſound an Alarm in my holy Mountain: Let all the Inhabitants of the Land tremble, for the day of the Lord cometh, for it is nigh at hand, <bibl>
                  <hi>Joel 2.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed: And are to be ſold by <hi>Dan. Browne</hi> at the <hi>Black-Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER,</head>
            <p>AMongſt great, many, and frequent Dangers, 'tis a Bleſſing to have Warning given, and to take it; for by theſe means, Evil may be prevented. This World is like a Wilderneſs, full of fiery Serpents, and other hurtful things, which on all Sides, we are compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and <hi>can one go upon hot Coals, and his Feet not be burnt?</hi> Which ſhould put us in mind of the Prophet's Queſtion, <hi>Who</hi> can or <hi>ſhall dwell with everlaſting burnings?</hi> Which in Hell ſhall be a Puniſhment for Sins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted here, if not pardoned in the way to Salvation. We have Enemies within and without: Our Heart is falſe, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions ſtrong, the World wicked, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations common and powerful, the Devil is ſubtle, and Sin deceitful, which all to reſiſt, we muſt Repent, Believe and Pray for converting, confirming and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining
<pb facs="tcp:172914:4"/>Grace. This, <hi>Reader,</hi> is my advice and warning to you: You ſhall know more after the peruſal of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Sheets. <hi>Remember that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance, no remiſſion of Sins, and as without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, ſo without Holineſs, no Man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>THey are very few, whereof the Firſt and Fourth are material, which the Reader may be pleaſed to Correct with a Pen.</p>
            <p>In Page 5. line 8. inſtead of <hi>care not,</hi> read <hi>take care,</hi> Page 11. line 21. read <hi>plaiſter,</hi> for <hi>plaiſtering,</hi> Page 56. line 2. <hi>friendly</hi> for <hi>friend,</hi> Page 64. laſt line <hi>aſſoon</hi> for <hi>alſo,</hi> Page 79. line 17. for <hi>War,</hi> read <hi>Warrant,</hi> Page 104. line 9. for <hi>earth</hi> read <hi>land.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172914:4"/>
            <head>THE TRUMPET IN SION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CRY aloud, ſpare not,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.1.</note> lift up thy voice like a Trumpet, and ſhew my people their Tranſgreſſions, and the houſe of Jacob their Sins:</hi> Theſe are the Words of Eternal and Almighty God to a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, who was conſiderable not ſo much for his extraordinary Parts and Royal Extraction (for he was the Son of <hi>Amos,</hi> Brother to <hi>Azariah</hi> King of <hi>Judah</hi>) as for the Excellency of the ſignal Viſions and Revelations, which the Lord was pleaſed to honour him with; and he being dead yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to us. Seeing all God's Actions are ſo wiſe, and ſo juſt, we muſt conceive ſuch an expreſs and poſitive Order not to be given without a weighty Cauſe, for God never in vain employs his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, nor indeed none of his Creatures, which <hi>are all his Servants.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.91.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172914:5"/>
            <p>The Occaſion of this Commiſſion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to the Prophet, was at that time a Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Sins among the People, whereof Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy and want of Charity were ſome of the chief: but though by their ſhews of Piety, as ſeeking God daily, drawing near unto him, Faſting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they impoſed upon Men, yet could not do ſo upon God, who will have his Prophet with diligence and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity to reprove Sinners for their Sins, though for ſome, more ſharply than for others. As for me, thô I be no Prophet, nor Son of a Prophet, yet I thank God, Prophets are no ſtrangers to me, for I daily am converſant with Prophets and with Apoſtles too, out of whoſe Writings, after ſeveral worthy Perſons, whoſe heart God hath ſtirred up to appear againſt the great and many Sins of the Times, as 'tis every one's Duty in his ſtation to do, I hope I may give in my Evidence: 'Tis a great Work that requires many hands, <hi>Multorum manibus, grande levatur onus.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God makes uſe of ſeveral inſtruments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable in themſelves, in different ways to carry on his works, thô all be tending to the ſame end; and although through the perverſeneſs of Mens hearts, the Effect doth not always anſwer the Deſign,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2.5.</note> yet <hi>they ſhall know, that there hath been,</hi> if not <hi>a Prophet among them,</hi> yet an Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher who hath given warning. May the Lord be pleaſed to bleſs with ſucceſs, the weak Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of all that are deſirous to promote his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſervice with the good of Souls, and to enlarge the Kingdom of Chriſt, in a time when we ſee the Sins of all Ages, of all Nations and in all kinds, more and more diſcovered and practiſed among us;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>From the ſole of the Foot unto the head,</hi> as the ſame Prophet complains of, here the Diſeaſe is become Epidemical, and its Fits very frequent, if not continual.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172914:5"/>
            <p>The houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> wanted being told of their Sins, ſo doth <hi>England,</hi> thô told often, but who can tell the number, diverſity, and frequency of them? However, I by the grace of God, ſhall endeavour to run over the moſt palpable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous: I ſhall ſpeak firſt of the Sins, after of the Puniſhments, according to God's threatning, due and inflicted for them. The Sins are of two general Kinds, ſome in Doctrine, others in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, otherwiſe called Error and Vice. Errors in Judgment are uſually followed by thoſe in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</p>
            <p>As Sin is extended over every Faculty of the Soul and Member of the Body, ſo there are Sins ſeated in the Mind as well as there are in the Heart, as indeed without a ſound Mind, the Heart can hardly be Sound: When the Soul's Eye is blind, how great muſt her darkneſs be? The miſtakes of the Underſtanding, which commonly from the <hi>Latin</hi> word are named Error, are by the <hi>Greeks</hi> called <hi>Hereſie,</hi> relating to Religious Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which is a diviſion in the Church cauſed by ſome erroneous Opinion againſt the Fundamentals of Religion: And thô all ſuch be bad enough, yet ſome there are worſe then others, according as they more or leſs ſtrike at the Root of Chriſtian Religion: Thoſe <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>perverſe things,</hi> and <hi>Doctrines of Devils,</hi> and <hi>Peter, Damnable Hereſies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 30. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note> Now there is in <hi>England,</hi> too many of thoſe as ſtrike at the very Foundation of our Holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Here are <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> not that properly ſpeaking any can be ſuch, for there is no Man in the World, but at one time or other, hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf convictions that there is a God, for ſuch a degree of Knowledge is naturally in Men:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172914:6"/>Hence it is that there was never in the World ſo Barbarian and Ignorant a Nation, but owned and worſhipped ſome Divinity or other; for 'tis only <hi>the fool</hi> that <hi>ſaith in his heart there is no God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 14.1.</note> yet he is not ſuch a Fool as to publiſh it, for he da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not for ſhame, but ſaith it in his Heart, where againſt the Light of Nature and Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Conſcience, he would ſmother the ſenſe of a Godhead, becauſe he wiſhes it. But the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> I mean, are thoſe who ſpeak and live as if there was no God, and theſe I may well call worſe then <hi>David</hi>'s Fool, for they blunder out Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal words, indirectly hinting that there is no God: Giddily, Impiouſly, Prophanely and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſtriking if not at the Being, yet at his Attributes, Works, Word and Providence, expreſs it in their Diſcourſes and Coverſation, and ſome in their Writings, whereby they ſeduce and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Judgment of ſome, influence the Weak, and give a great Scandal to thoſe who fear God and have an awful reverence for his Holy Name, when they happen to hear them in their Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal fits. This is a preſumptuous and defying Sin, which among us too many are guilty of; ſuch teach the way to Hell, and were taught in the School of <hi>Vanninus</hi> and of ſuch abominable Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; for he who owns not the true God, and hath not the right Notion of and due Reverence for him, is as if he believed no God. This is ſo odious and ſhameful, that Men take it as a great Injury to be call'd <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and thô the thing be really in them, yet hate to be call'd by its Name; and we have cauſe to remember, how becauſe the Title of a Bill was <hi>againſt Atheiſm, &amp;c.</hi> great exceptions were taken againſt it, as of a great ſtain upon the Nation, that we thereby ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to Foreign Countries how we have <hi>Atheiſts</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172914:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>among us, which is too true, thô ſome, whom there is cauſe to ſuſpect to be ſuch, would not have it ſaid: But I would have ſuch to anſwer me one queſtion, Which of theſe two brings a greater Scandal and Reproach to <hi>England,</hi> either not to forbear ſaying we have <hi>Atheiſts</hi> when we have, and not to puniſh them, or elſe to own the Truth, that we have ſome, but care not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain and puniſh them? <hi>David</hi> declareth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 53.1.</note> that where abominable Iniquity is committed and no regard had to Virtue or Vice, there is no God.</p>
            <p>Next we have the <hi>Deiſts,</hi> whoſe Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts only in acknowledging one God, and think that is enough to be Saved: Who thô they own a God, yet fancy him to be other then he is, and to act otherwiſe then he doth; they are for a Natural Religion without and againſt Revealed, they think all Religions to be equal, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one is at liberty to chuſe which he pleaſes, and that he may be ſaved in any.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idolatry</hi> is another Sin of the Nation; I mean not only the Spiritual one of thoſe whoſe God is their Riches, Honour, Pleaſures, and their Belly, but groſs and material Idolatry of thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Religious Worſhip to be due to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and actually render it, and in too many Places there are too many Books that juſtifie it. I thank God, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> here are not of that O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but <hi>Papiſt,</hi> are, own and practiſe it; and that Abomination is in the ſight of all ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Land, which is thereby defiled. Prieſts, contrary to Laws, do every where, even out of Foreign Parts ſwarm as much as ever, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> are as free as can be, whilſt poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> againſt the Laws of their Country, are barbarouſly Perſecuted in <hi>Popiſh</hi> Dominions; yet one would think we might ſomewhat better their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172914:7"/>with threatning here <hi>Papiſts</hi> with the like Uſage, I ſhall not ſay as to Liberties and Lives, (for our Religion, like theirs, doth not bind us to be Sanguinary) but as to Eſtates and Fortunes; with our Neglecting to take the ſame care to Defend our Religion, as they do to Promote theirs, we ſeem to intimate that theirs is better than ours; but if we, whoſoever we are, under the Notion that we are not Perſecutors, be aſhamed of Chriſt and of his Cauſe, in his due time he will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of and diſown us; I may ſay, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the time when here it was not ſo. Is it not the height of impudence for Popiſh Prieſts to go (as of late they have done) to dying Men,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>To Doctor</hi> Connor.</note> after they by Proteſtant Miniſters had been prepared for Death, to diſquiet them, and not give over till they had made them do what upon ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions is uſual for Papiſts; yet this hath been win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at, no inquiry made, no examination taken againſt thoſe who ſo notoriouſly break the Laws of the Land. The following Paper in French was on a Lord's Day, <hi>April</hi> 24. 1698. poſted up over the French Chapel door in <hi>St. James</hi>'s, and other Places, in theſe words, <hi>Hereby notice is given, that in caſe any French Refugee, be willing to go back into</hi> France, <hi>there to abjure Hereſie, he may addreſs himſelf to the</hi> French <hi>Ambaſſador, and according to his Quality he ſhall be rewarded:</hi> By this beginning we may ſee what we muſt expect from his being here; one would think ſuch things ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to his Inſtructions or Commiſſion; but what would they ſay if our Ambaſſador in <hi>Paris</hi> had attempted any thing of the like nature. Never till of late any Foreign Miniſter was allowed two Popiſh Chapels, one Private for Himſelf and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, which no Man will queſtion, and to the great grief of many, another Publick one, for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172914:7"/>all that have a mind to come to't, with Four or Five Prieſts belonging to it; and neither Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive nor Executive Powers would take any notice of it; but God will in his due time, and may be puniſh us by ſuch Snakes as we keep in our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom.</p>
            <p>For theſe many years together, we have had very near this City a <hi>Nunnery</hi> hitherto undiſturbed; and one more, near about the ſame diſtance, but another way, is a forming, or rather already for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Another <hi>Maſs</hi>-Chapel in Town, is as much frequented by hundreds at this time, as it was when in the hands of <hi>Benedictine</hi> Friars. And now Prieſts to ſeduce People, as much as ever do transform themſelves into all ſhapes, and too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten do prevail upon Servants, Prentices, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters too: Yet by the Laws it is Treaſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice any one to be reconciled to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, as well as to be reconciled to't. But as yet it doth not appear that any effectual care hath been taken to hinder that great Evil, and to prevent this Venom of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Idolatry from ſpreading far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the Ruine and Deſtruction of precious Souls, the Scandal of Religion, and Shame of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> unhappily we have here: <hi>Socinians</hi> who would be called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> and others, have in every poſſible way taken great care to infect the Nation, and ſpread among us their Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Opinions againſt the moſt <hi>Holy Trinity;</hi> they are ſo well known by their impious Doctrines and unwarrantable Practices to propagate them, that there is no need any longer to mention them here in this Place. 'Tis pity they have not been taken notice of in the way of Puniſhment, as in their preſumptuous Offences againſt God's Cauſe. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Blaſphemers as execrable as can be,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172914:8"/>do impiouſly in their Diſcourſes ridicule the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Myſtery of the Incarnation, our Saviour's Birth of a Virgin, the Holy Scripture, and the whole Chriſtian Religion, which they call Prieſt-Craft, a Forgery of Melancholick Brains, and ſuch other abominable things, as makes one's Hair ſtand on end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Libertiniſm</hi> is here promoted by a Sect call'd <hi>Antinomians,</hi> who Believe, as if Men might go to Heaven in the way to Hell, without Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and new Obedience; thus no neceſſity of good Works; and all this becauſe we are ſaid to be Saved thorough Grace, which is moſt True, and indeed excludes Good Works from being the meritorious Cauſe of Salvation, but not from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing means and way to it; for he who created us without us, will not Save us without us.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo a kind of <hi>Free-willers,</hi> who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſtrike at God's free Grace in Chriſt, and I dare ſay, are as much againſt it, as <hi>Socinians</hi> are againſt his Perſon. Sins againſt God's Juſtice, his Truth and other Attributes are great, but I look upon Sin againſt his Grace, as one of the greateſt and leſs pardonable.</p>
            <p>Here we have a Monſtrous Sect call'd <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers;</hi> Monſtrous I call it, for its Doctrine is a Rhapſody of Errors in ſeveral kinds; they have troubled the World with a number of idle Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, containing a confuſed heap of Spiritual and Natural Ignorance; full of Nonſenſe, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, wreſting and miſapplying of Holy Scripture, and a meer racking of good Senſe and ſound Reaſon, which is able to diſguſt any Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Man from Reading them, as I confeſs, I ſoon was; but ſome who made it their Buſineſs to go throughly with them, have therein found ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Pernicious, Impious and Blaſphemous Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172914:8"/>drawn out of their Writings, which they have Publiſhed and ſet their Names to't. This I may ſay of <hi>Quakers,</hi> that to themſelves they aſſume the Name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but in my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, without True grounds: For they own no other Chriſt, but him whom they ſay to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, whom they make ſpeak any thing they pleaſe; then they are not Baptized in the Name of Chriſt, whoſe Ordinances they Reject and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, for they own no Sacraments, deny Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry by way of Office in the Church, which is the Houſe of the God of Order; yet all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therein, but what is of their own making, they would deſtroy, and condemn All that are not of their own Perſuaſion, uſurping only to themſelves the name of <hi>God's People;</hi> withal, in their Worldly Concerns they are Cunning and Crafty, Buſie and Active, Thriving and Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, medling with many Things, with a Stock of ready Money to ſupply their Occaſions, and carry on their common Intereſt in the World: The Government hath thought fit to give them a Toleration; I wiſh they do not prove a Snake in its Boſom, for they are as dangerous to the State as to the Church. Certainly 'tis a great Sin to ſuffer them to Diſhonour God through their Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, as 'tis in them to do't.</p>
            <p>Several other Hereſies and Errors in Doctrine we have here, whereof ſome are more, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers leſs known, Who can tell them all? But all, thô in different Degrees, are contrary to Goſpel Truths; and thô winked at, are to be reckoned among the ſinful Opinions and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in the Nation.</p>
            <p>But as the Nation is infected with many Sins in the Mind, ſo 'tis full of others ſeated in the Heart, wherein is the Spring of all ſinful Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172914:9"/>
               <hi>For,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.19.</note> ſaith our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>out of the heart proceed evil thoughts,</hi> or deſires, <hi>murthers, adulteries fornications, thefts, falſe witneſs, blaſphemies.</hi> This leads us to the Second Branch of the great and many Sins of the Nation which conſiſt in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; and upon this Head, with <hi>David</hi> I may ſay, thô very ſhort of what the thing deſerves, <hi>Rivers of water run down mine eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.136.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they keep not thy Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sins properly lodged in the Heart, are Firſt <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> a damnable Sin in this World, and accordingly to be rewarded in that which is to come;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.51.</note> for, <hi>there is a portion for hypocrites,</hi> who indeed can ſometimes diſſemble with and impoſe upon Men, but not ſo with God: The Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite is Squint-ey'd, and thô he looks one way yet like the Waterman Row's towards a quite contrary. It is bad upon all accounts; but in Matters of Religion, abominable, like the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> as our Saviour with many a <hi>Woe</hi> tells them, <hi>they are like unto whited Sepulchres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.23, 24, 25. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>which indeed appear beautiful outward, but are within full of dead mens bones; and of all uncleanneſs;</hi> an outward ſhew of Piety and Virtue, but in reality are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs: <hi>They ſtrain at a Gnat and ſwallow a Camel.</hi> and <hi>outwardly appear righteous unto Men, but within are full of hypocriſie and iniquity.</hi> The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Poet could ſay of ſuch, <hi>Qui Curios ſimulant ſed Bacchanalia vivunt.</hi> In ſome things of the leaſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they would ſeem to be Pious and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; <hi>they pay tithe of Mint, of Aniſe, and Cumin, but omit the weightier matters of the Law;</hi> like the <hi>Jews,</hi> who upon the preparation day of the paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 18.28.</note> 
               <hi>would not go into the Judgment-Hall, leſt they ſhould be defiled,</hi> but made no Conſcience to ſhed innocent Blood, and to cry out <hi>Crucifie, Crucifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172914:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Vanity</hi> is another Sin of the Heart,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 7.22.</note> or <hi>it proceedeth out of it;</hi> of it I make but one Sin, for a Proud Man is a Vain Man; Pride is the Sin of the Devil, and of our Firſt Parents, now too natural with many among us, who look ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry big upon others, as if they were not Fleſh, Blood and Corruption, as well as other Men, yet they are not made of a Matter of a different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of what others are; they came into the World like other Men, ſhall Die and be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture for Worms as well as others. Some are proud of their Riches, which, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>certainly they make themſelves wings and fly away as an Eagle;</hi> others are proud of their Honours, which in a ſhort time are laid in the Duſt; others of their Pleaſures, for they have all that Heart can wiſh, ſo had <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in the great Feaſt he made to a Thouſand of his Lords, to his Wives and Concubines;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.5.6.</note> but <hi>in the ſame Hour came forth fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of a Man's hand, and wrote over againſt the Candleſtick upon the plaiſtering of the Wall of the King's Palace. Then the King's countenance was changed, and his thoughts troubled him, ſo that the joints of his loins were looſed, and his knees ſmote one againſt another, and in that night was the King ſlain.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 30. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1.</note> Others are proud of their Parts, as Wit, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for <hi>knowledge puffeth up;</hi> for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, thoſe parts they prophane, and make a wrong uſe of: Others are proud of their Strength, Comlineſs, Beauty, and ſuch Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Endowments; but to all ſuch, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>What haſt thou that thou didſt not receive?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>now if thou didſt receive it, why doſt thou glory as if thou hadſt not received it?</hi> Be thankful for what thou haſt received, and Glory not in thy ſelf, or in thine own Shame, but <hi>glory in the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 1 31.</note> Pride is a Sin odious to God and Man, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172914:10"/>none was ever the better,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.13.</note> but many have been the worſe for. <hi>The fear of the Lord is to hate evil, pride and arrogancy,</hi> &amp;c. Saith the Son of God, under the name of Wiſdom;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.18 <hi>Chad.</hi> 3.</note> and <hi>when Pride cometh then cometh Shame;</hi> it alſo <hi>goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſtruction.</hi> Therefore ſaith the Prophet, <hi>The pride of thine heart hath deceived thee,</hi> not only to <hi>Moab,</hi> but alſo to every one that is proud; for <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.23.</note> who is Juſt, <hi>plentifully rewardeth the proud doer.</hi> And we have the teſtimony of Two Apoſtles for this Truth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.6. and 5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5.</note> that <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble.</hi> Certainly that Sin ſhall not go unpuniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vanity</hi> doth conſtantly attend Pride: Proud People are vain, and ſometimes extravagant in their Food, Apparel, Diſcourſes, Expences, and whole Carriage; 'tis a Fume which from the Heart flies up into the Head, and makes thoſe who therewith are affected, Giddy, Odious, and Ridiculous to a ſtander by: and as this is their weak part, ſo by the diſcovery they make of it, they lie open to the Attempts of all that to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour them, will flatter them in their Vanity. <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s vain Glory in ſhewing the King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi>'s Ambaſſador all his Treaſures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 39.67.</note> was moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed, and by the grievouſneſs of the puniſhment (for all thoſe things were afterwards carried to <hi>Babylon</hi>) 'tis demonſtrated how much God doth Hate and Deteſt Pride and vain Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>From Pride and Vanity flows <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Vices, for <hi>Oria dant vitia.</hi> A proud and vain Man thinks it to be below himſelf to do any thing, ſcorneth to ſet his hand about any Work; which he would look upon as a diſparagement unto himſelf; rather Steal, Rob, Cheat, and Starve than to Work, being intoxicated with a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172914:10"/>Chimerical Opinion of Abilities, Merits, Birth, and Quality: Hence it is, that often we ſee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral to miſcarry in what they undertake, becauſe they take it to be beneath them. Pride and Idleneſs we find reckoned among the Sins of abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>Sodom,</hi> for, <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.49.</note> 
               <hi>this was the iniquity of thy Siſter</hi> Sodom, <hi>Pride, fulneſs of Bread, and abundance of Idleneſs was in her, and in her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Her terrible puniſhment ſhould make eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one tremble that is partaker of her Sins.</p>
            <p>Under this Head of Idleneſs, ſome things I may reduce, which being not evil in themſelves, and moderately uſed, may well enough be allowed, chiefly when there is with it a Bodily Exerciſe; but when abuſed, become evil by accident, as when there is too much Coſt and Time beſtow'd upon't: Such are <hi>Play-houſes</hi> when too often fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented; (ſuppoſe the Stages were Chaſte and Pure, as they are not) What Exceſs is it to give ſo much Money to a <hi>French</hi> Dancer, to an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Singer, who when they are full of Money, will go home and Laugh at us for it: I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forget what once I heard <hi>Harlequin</hi> (give me leave to name him,) ſay upon the Stage, having ſaid ſomething which made all People Laugh; he added, Who hath cauſe to Laugh, you, who part with your Money, or I who get it? Such alſo are ſo many <hi>Lotteries,</hi> which afford occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of much Cheating and Tricking, whereby greedineſs of Getting, and ſomething of Infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſqueeze out of Peoples Purſes that Money which might be better beſtowed upon their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary occaſions. Such are alſo <hi>Races,</hi> upon which ſome loſe ſometimes Hundreds, nay Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Pounds, beſides Charges they are at in keeping their Horſes, when they will deny a poor Perſon One Peny ask'd for God's and for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172914:11"/>Chriſt's ſake, to keep them from Starving; and a Creditor One Shiling, towards Payment of Debt. Is not this a Sin, and a great One too? I ſhall but name Hunting, Hawking, Courſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which, thô indifferent and tolerable enough in themſelves, yet when too much time, which might better be beſtowed, is ſpent upon't, become ſinful: <hi>Actaeon</hi>'s Fable ſuggeſts that when that Sport goes beyond the bounds of a Bodily Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and of a neceſſary Recreation, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a violent and unſatiable Paſſion, he that is poſſeſſed with it, is ſometimes ruin'd, and eaten up by his Dogs, which Sport leads him to ſee naked Nymphs, which haſten his Deſtruction: And to ſpeak the beſt of it, I wiſh Men to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how <hi>Diana</hi> the Hunting Queen was Chaſte, but Barren, ſo produced nothing,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> well call'd <hi>Idolatry</hi> in Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.5.</note> for Riches are the Covetous Man's Idol God, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>the root of all evil;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</note> for the love of Money puts Men and Women upon all wicked Deſigns and Attempts: Hence ſpring Injuſtice, not to pay Debts, and give every one their own, Violence, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Extortion, Cheats; in few words, 'tis the breach of the whole Law: The Covetous like the Swine, doth much harm, but no body good till he be dead; he is the wicked and unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant, who burieth the Talent, and with it doth others no good nor himſelf neither, for as he deprives them of their due, ſo he denies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not only Conveniencies, but alſo Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. We have ſome who accumulate Sins, for they are both Proud and Covetous: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Men will bear with ones Pride if he be liberal; and with his Covetouſneſs if he be Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Meek: But he who is both Proud and Covetous, is hated of all.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:172914:11"/>
            <p>The Vice oppoſite to that, namely <hi>Prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> is alſo ſeated in the Heart, which might ſeem a <hi>Paradox,</hi> as is to have contrary things lodged in one and the ſame Subject, were it not that in the Heart are ſo many places, ſeveral windings and turnings. This Sin I look upon as a branch or effect of Pride and Vanity, for out of this Principle, and for the end of being ſeen and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded by Men, ſome are profuſe, and unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily beſtow Coſts upon their Luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more Sins there are in the Heart, as all inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Affections which come under what Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers call <hi>Appetites,</hi> either <hi>iraſcible</hi> or <hi>concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcible,</hi> which I ſhall omit ſpeaking of, that I may come to Sins in practice, which the Nation is ſo much Affected Infected, and Overgrown with, to the Diſhonour of God, wrong and prejudice of the Neighbours, Shame and Infamy of the Guilty: <hi>Hinc dolor hinc lachrymae:</hi> Where ſhall I begin, and how ſhall I make an end? there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a number and variety of them.</p>
            <p>About Sins in <hi>Practice,</hi> I ſhall begin with thoſe which directly are levell'd againſt GOD; ſo ſhall follow with thoſe that alſo are (but indire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly) againſt GOD; for one way or other, every Sin is againſt GOD, but immediately againſt Men, and deſtructive to Human Society: But as this would prove a long Task, I ſhall mention only the moſt Common and Notorious. And Firſt, We have too many of thoſe who would ridicule Grace, and, thinking it to be a piece of Wit, Impiouſly and Prophanely to carp at God's Word and Works, and in their Diſcourſes, as well as in their Lives, to make a mock at Sin. But who are thoſe? not the Wiſe, except it be in their own Conceit; but Fools, for long ago, by <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Pen, God hath proclaimed them for ſuch,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172914:12"/>when he ſaid <hi>Fools make a mock at Sin;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.9</note> now in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s and <hi>David</hi>'s ſtile, the Fool is the Wicked Man, who at the latter end, ſhall appear to be the greateſt Fool of all: No jeſting with Holy Things, nor with <hi>God,</hi> who <hi>will not be mockt;</hi> and Men who believe otherwiſe are much deceived; and if their Conſcience tells them not before, ſhall at laſt find they were ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sabbath-breaking</hi> is one of the Chief and Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Sins of the Nation: Every one that can read Scripture may know how ſtrict and ſevere God was againſt <hi>Sabbath-breakers;</hi> by his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate command they were
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.32, 35.</note> 
               <hi>ſtoned</hi> to death. The holy Obſervation of that day, was what he moſtly required of that People, not only now and then, here and there, but he made it the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the firſt Table of the Law; greatly complain'd of the breach thereof, and ſeverely puniſh'd it upon Perſons, and the whole Nation. There is the ſame reaſon for the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, in Scripture call'd the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Lord's Day;</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral breakers thereof, God hath in the Chriſtian Church made Examples of his Judgments. A great one we had in this Nation, of that Prince, who at ſeveral times, having with Stage-Plays polluted the Lord's-Day, and by means of a Book of Sports, allowed and encouraged others to do ſo, was out of the ſame Place where he had ſeen them acted, brought upon the Scaffold, where he loſt his Life. I do not pretend to dive into the ſecret Cauſes of God's Judgments, but I muſt take notice how the Circumſtance of the Place is very remarkable, and we may be allowed to ſay how upon that Ground, as well as upon others,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 76.12.</note> 
               <hi>God is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Kings of the Earth.</hi> This is Matter of Fact: Thô in his Son's Reign Piety was little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, yet then we ſaw Acts of Parliament for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172914:12"/>the better Obſervation of the Lord's-Day, to come out; but now 'tis thought not to be worth looking after: in
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>That of</hi> 29 Ch. II. 1677.</note> one of thoſe Acts, <hi>the Sale of any Wares, Merchandizes, Fruits, Herbs, Goods or Chattels whatſoever, upon the Lord's Day, or any part thereof,</hi> was forbidden, <hi>upon pain that every Perſon ſo offending, ſhall forfeit the ſame Goods ſo cryed, or ſhewed forth, or expoſed to ſale.</hi> Sabbaths were never more prophan'd then of late and now: The generality of People make Play and Sport Days of them, On that day we ſee Markets ſet up in many Places, Children publickly at play; Taverns, Alehouſes, Coffee and Chocolate-Houſes doors open and full of People: and thoſe Beaſts, which in the 4th Precept God had a regard to, muſt not reſt upon that day, though upon every other in the Week, they labour with all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hardneſs, which is a Cruelty, for
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>a righteous man regardeth the life of his beaſt.</hi> Yet theſe muſt be for the Service of many Sabbath-breakers: When the Drunkard is ſo fuddled that he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reeling and Staggering cannot go, he muſt have a Coach to carry him home. We have but one true Chriſtian Holy-day, which ought to be employ'd only for Holy uſes. He who makes no Conſcience to break the Lord's Holiday, will make no Scruple of breaking any of the Ten Commandments; and he who delights to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, will the uſe Authority to make others ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it too, 'Tis ſtrange, yet true, that ſome who in the Church have been and ſtill are moſt fond after the reading of every Commandment, of the fourth as well as of every one elſe, to ſay. <hi>Lord have merey upon us, and incline our hearts to keep this law,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Pocklington, Heylin,</hi> and the Higheſt Church-men, in their Writings, Sermons, and Diſcourſes, declared much againſt the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172914:13"/>of the Sabbath or Lord's-Day, how then can they pray to God to incline their Heart to keep a Law which they believe and profeſs to be abrogated? But if herein one was to conſult with Man's Opinion, beſides the Judgment of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Divines, that of the good Pious and Learned <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> is with me of greater weight then the Authority of all <hi>Anti-Sabbatharians,</hi> and all know how much in his judgment and practice, he was for the ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Lord's Day. One thing more, though by the by, and not to my preſent purpoſe, I ſhall obſerve out of the Words, <hi>Incline our Hearts to keep this Law,</hi> it appears how the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of thoſe who compiled the Common-Prayer-Book and appointed theſe words to be ſaid after every Precept, was, that Men cannot incline their Hearts to keep God's Law, but muſt pray to God to do't, and conſequently that to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and obey, doth not depend upon Man's Will, but upon God's working upon and inclining it.</p>
            <p>There is another crying Sin in the Nation, which hath ſeveral branches, as <hi>Lying, Swearing, Curſing,</hi> and <hi>Perjury.</hi> We have a ſort of People who in this kind offend in the leaſt Degree, yet thereby contract a Guilt upon themſelves; out of an ill Habit and Cuſtom, upon moſt or any trivial account, ſaying, <hi>O Lord, O God,</hi> which is to take that Holy Name in vain, and a Breach of the Third Commandment: But others worſe, impiouſly take the Lord by his Bloud, Wounds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſwear by the Creatures; 'tis abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſometimes to hear in the Streets, Children of Eight and Ten years old and upwards, to Curſe and Damn themſelves and others, which ought to be the Care of Parents to prevent; a horrid Sin; God hath given us a Tongue to Bleſs not to Curſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172914:13"/>him, nor our Neighbour, or our ſelves, yet ſome, as ſoon as they are able to ſpeak, rap out Oaths. A Curſe in God's Name never falls without an Effect either againſt the Curſer or Curſed. That abominable Sin of <hi>Perjury,</hi> and Swearing falſly in God's Name is too common. <hi>Forſwearing, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-breaking and Burning,</hi> are ſo grievous a Sin, as that in every judgment we undergo, we may therein ſee a Grain of it, as the Jews did in theirs, in relation to the Golden Calf.</p>
            <p>The Sin of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs</hi> is Loud and Epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal in its ſeveral branches of Fornication and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery; and there is too much cauſe to name <hi>Inceſt</hi> and <hi>Sodomy,</hi> for which the Earth affords no ſufficient Puniſhment; therefore, in Fire and Brimſtone, God, as it were, rained down Hell from Heaven upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is among People of all Conditions, Ages, and Kinds, now as common, frequent, and publick, as between Dogs and Bitches, without Curb and Reſtraint put upon't, ſo that Whoredom is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly one of the Maſter Sins of the Nation: Bawdy-Houſes are tolerated, and, even in high Places, want no Advocates to ſpeak for them; at any time, ſpecially towards the Evening, one can hardly go up and down the Street but he meets with Inticements and Temptations: Sometimes an honeſt Woman, who goes about her neceſſary buſineſs, can hardly paſs ſafely and undiſturbed through the Streets; and ſome of that Sex that proſtitute themſelves, in ſome times of the Night walk in their Meeting-places, and wander up and down the Streets, when <hi>Bridewell</hi> ſhould be filled with them. But we muſt leave this filthy Subject, which defiles Thoughts. Tongue, and Pen, and as well as Swearing and Perjury, have of late in ſome
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Tracts</hi> been ſet out in their own Colours
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172914:14"/>and only give a Hint of an idle Vanity of ſome Men and Women, who in order to pleaſe others, to excite Luſt, and ſatisfie their Corrupt Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, do ſtand or ſit whole Hours before a Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs, there to admire themſelves, like ſo many <hi>Narciſſus</hi>'s in love with their Faces. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not blame Men or Women for ſeeing every thing about them to be well, decently, and cleanly, but far from this neceſſary Care are the foppiſh and vain Attire and meer Trinkets, as Patches, Painting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> too much uſed by ſome for ill ends.</p>
            <p>Concerning this Head, before I leave it off, I muſt farther take notice, how there are too many kinds of Houſes ſubſervient to this Sin, as firſt <hi>Bawdy</hi>-Houſes, kept up meerly for that purpoſe, or <hi>Stews,</hi> by <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. for ever forbidden in <hi>England.</hi> 'Tis a great ſhame that in a Chriſtian State Reformed, or pretending, from the abuſes of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, in Doctrine and Practices, ſuch Places ſhould be known and ſuffered: We <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſay, and 'tis very true, that the <hi>Pope</hi> and thoſe under him in <hi>Rome,</hi> receive Money for tolerating ſuch Wickedneſſes, under the pretence, that 'tis to avoid a more horrid Sin, as if God had allowed to chuſe and exchange Sins, and ſo diſpenſed Men from the ſtrict Obſervation of his Law: And I am afraid, here we have ſome who againſt their Duty and Oath, take Fees not to diſturb thoſe Infamous Places. Here alſo are ſome Places which we may call <hi>Game</hi>-Houſes, where are play'd more than one ſort of Game, to the Ruine of the Souls of ſome, Young and Old, and Laviſhing the Eſtates of others, and this by ſuch Perſons, as the Land ſhould vomit out into their own: Alſo there are <hi>Chocolate</hi>-Houſes with Private Rooms, which though frequented by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172914:14"/>ſome Perſons of Honour and Virtue, yet are look'd upon as meeting Places for Vice, Idleneſs, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Diſcourſes, and other ſinful Practices. And we hear, of late are ſprung out of Hell, Houſes for the execrable Seed of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> who could have believed it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> is a great and common Sin, which deprives Men of the uſe of Reaſon, and makes them, I ſhall not ſay like unto, but worſe then Beaſts, which, do what you can, you are never able to make to drink, if they be not thirſty: The uſe of Liquor is to quench one's Thirſt, but when 'tis abuſed, through God's Judgment, it cauſes a contrary Effect, for it inflames and makes one drier and drier. The <hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> to make that Vice odious to their Children, made their Slaves Drunk, and then expoſed them to their ſight: And <hi>Lyeurgus</hi> being asked, why in his Laws he had appointed no puniſhment for Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards? ſaid, <hi>Drunkenneſs carries its puniſhment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it;</hi> the Head-ake, the Pain in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, violent Vomiting, Inflammation of the Blood, with many other Symptoms that attend it, do ſufficiently demonſtrate its Malignity: And if a Drunken Man could but well ſee his dull or wandering Eyes, the redneſs or paleneſs of his Face, his wry Mouth, Crabbed Looks, ſmell the Stink of what comes up out of his Stomach, as out of a Dog's, and hear the Stammerings and Stut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings of his Tongue, perceive his Reeling and Staggerings, in a word, how much he looks like a ſtinking and a ſilly Fool, he would be aſhamed of himſelf and of his Vice; beſides the danger of Breaking his Neck, or ſome Limb, when he is Drunk, or doing himſelf and others ſome Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief when his Drink turns into Fury and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as we daily have a ſad Experience of it, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172914:15"/>'tis too uſual with ſome; or elſe being tumbled into a Feaver or ſome ſuch violent Diſtemper, or at laſt being beſotted, for continual Drinking drowns what good natural Parts a Man may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to have either by Nature or acquired by Labour and Induſtry.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.29, 30, 31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath wo? Who hath ſorrow?</hi> ſaith the Wiſe man, <hi>Who hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention? who hath babbling? who hath wounds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe? who hath redneſs of eyes:</hi> He anſwers, <hi>They that tarry long at the Wine; They that go to ſeek mixt wine.</hi> His advice followeth, <hi>Look not thou upon the wine when it is red, when it giveth its colour in the cup, when it moveth it ſelf aright; ar the laſt it biteth like a Serpent, and ſtingeth like an Adder.</hi> Theſe are the Effects of Drunkenneſs, yet ſome are ſo infatuated as to delight in fuddling themſelves and others: Againſt ſuch the Prophet pronounces a
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Wo unto him that giveth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour drink, that putteſt his bottle to him, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt him drunken alſo.</hi> There muſt be a Venom in the Fruit, when abuſed, which we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in the Tree that produces it, which is good for nothing elſe but to be burnt, for God ſaith ſo by the Prophet.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Son of man, what is the Vine tree more then any tree? Shall wood be taken thereof to do any work? or will men take a pin of it to hang any veſſel thereon. Behold it is caſt into the fire for fewel, the fire devoureth both the ends of it, and the middle of it is burnt: is it meet for any work?</hi> No; and Experience ſhews, it is of no uſe, only for the fire. Now Drunkenneſs is a Mother-ſin, for it cauſes many others, and indeed can produce any other, as <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> can witneſs. We read of one who when he was Sober, being asked which of theſe three things he would chuſe, either to be Drunken, to Lye with his Mother, or to Kill his Father; he rejected the two laſt as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172914:15"/>and abominable, and made choice of the firſt; but once he being Drunk, laid with his Mother when ſhe was aſleep, and kill'd his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upbraiding him for it.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 28.1.</note> 
               <hi>Woe to the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards of Ephraim,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, and others too, as well as to them. This Exceſs of ſome, and abuſe of the Creature, which God made to be uſed with Sobriety and Thankſgiving, makes it
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>groan and travail in pain till it be delivered from the bondage of corruption,</hi> which in their way Drunkards keep it under.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the moſt beaſtly and groſſeſt Sins in the Land; but there are of another kind more ſubtle and refined, which ſtick to the Soul more than to the Body. We read how in our Saviour's days, the Bodies of many were poſſeſſed of the Devil, but now when he hath a greater Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he is, to Man's greater harm, gone far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and poſſeſſes the Souls as much as ever he did the Bodies: Too many have Learn'd under that cunning and dangerous Maſter, and are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come great Proficients in his Art, and as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls it his
<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>Devices</hi> and his
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>Depths.</hi> Some of theſe I ſhall give a hint of.</p>
            <p>Certainly <hi>Injuſtice</hi> is one of the loudeſt and moſt crying Sins in the Nation, the Evil and Wickedneſs whereof we may unqueſtionably know, by its being directly oppoſed to one of God's Eſſential Attributes, for God is eſſentially Righteous and Juſt: And according to our power and meaſure we ought to endeavour to be ſuch, for as we muſt be Holy becauſe God is Holy, ſo we muſt be Juſt becauſe he is Juſt; that is, as near as we can we ought to conform to God. Nothing in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is more often and earneſtly commanded and commended than to be Juſt, as nothing more ſtrictly forbidden then Injuſtice, eſpecially to thoſe whom God hath appointed to adminiſter it. There are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172914:16"/>three ſorts of Juſtice, the <hi>Diſtributive, Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and <hi>Legal.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> conſiſts in the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of Rewards and Pains, and hath reſpect to the Dignity of Perſons, according to the Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical Proportion: It compoſes the whole with the part; that is the common Goods of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, beſtowing them upon thoſe who deſerve it beſt. The <hi>ſecond</hi> allows every Man his own, the Workman his Hire, the Servant his Wages, Soldiers their Pay: and it depends much upon agreements; thus a Nobleman is to pay the price of a Horſe as well as an ordinary Man, and it is according to the Numerical Proportion: It alſo doth compoſe one part with another, making one Citizen equal with another. The <hi>third</hi> is, that Juſtice which is according to Right and Law; it doth compoſe and fit the Part for the whole, making every particular Man contribute to the Common Good, and Private Intereſts, ſubſervient to the Publick and Great one.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis too true that in all theſe, there are wants and abuſes, and I leave it for thoſe who are concern'd, to examine themſelves about it. As to the firſt, There ſhould be Rewards and Puniſhments adequate to the Good and Evil done by Men; and I wiſh all Princes would but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſome of the laſt words of a great and good King, <hi>David</hi> I mean, who ſaid with a great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3.</note> 
               <hi>The God of Iſrael ſaid, the Rock of Iſrael ſpake to me, he that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God.</hi> Reward and Puniſh well, and God will be pleaſed, and you well ſerved, but to let ſome who deſerved well to Want and Starve, whilſt others that were very unworthy Men, receive abundantly to ſupply their Luſt, this I ſay is a great breach of <hi>Diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive</hi> Juſtice. As to the <hi>Commutative,</hi> how many
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172914:16"/>and great Abuſes about it there is in this our World: Some have forgotten, or mind not what our Bleſſed Saviour ſaid in his Sermon upon the Mount,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore all things whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them:</hi> And the more to perſuade them to't, he adds, <hi>for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> If when Men wrong others, they would but ſay to themſelves, Wouldeſt thou be content to be ſo uſed? Their Conſcience would fly into their Faces, Why then will not they give every one their own? Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral in the Kingdom, againſt Juſtice, Honour, and all Rules of Honeſty, make no Conſcience to take other Men's Goods, and not to pay for them, thô they have plentiful Eſtates, yet will not pay one Six-pence of Debts; rather beſtow it upon their own Luſt, Whoring, Gaming, Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Starving and Undoing of many Perſons, and whole Families, yet think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Priviledged to do ſo. Do ſuch People think there is no God in Heaven to hear
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>the cry of the hire of the Labourers which have reaped down their Fields.</hi> Of thoſe who ſold them their Wares and Goods, but cannot get one Farthing from them that always are ready to Buy, but never care to Pay; Certainly ſaith the Apoſtle, ſuch
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>cries are entred into the ears of the Lord of Sabbaoth.</hi> God heareth the Cries of the ſins of the wicked, to puniſh them for it; thus
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>the cry of thoſe of Sodom went up to God.</hi> He alſo heareth the
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>groaning</hi> and cry of the Afflicted and oppreſſed, as he <hi>did</hi> that of his People in <hi>Egypt.</hi> For ſaith the Lord to <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>The cry of the children of Iſrael is come unto me;</hi> thus <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>cry came before him, even into his ears:</hi> for indeed,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>(h) Pſal.</hi> 34.15.</note> 
               <hi>the eyes of the Lord are upon the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and his ears are open unto their cry,</hi> to avenge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172914:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:172914:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:172914:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:172914:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:172914:19"/>and deliver them. The <hi>Wicked</hi> and Oppreſſor is but a fool for his pains, to
<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſay in his heart, thou wilt not require it,</hi> for <hi>thou haſt ſeen it,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt, for thou beholdeſt miſchief and ſpite to requite it with thy hand, the poor committeth himſelf unto thee, for thou art the helper of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs.</hi> The helpleſs Man upon Earth hath a God in Heaven to go to.</p>
            <p>There are high degrees of this ſort of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, called <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>Extortion.</hi> Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is a vexation and tormenting a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or inferior Perſon by Violence and Authority; this is the ſin of Superiour Powers and Rulers: thus Tyrants oppreſs God's People, laying ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burthens of ſeveral ſorts upon them, as they are not able to bear, but are thereby preſſed down, and muſt ly under; in this God is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd, it being an abominable Abuſe of that Power and Authority which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſome over others, this, in <hi>David</hi>'s words is
<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.20.</note> 
               <hi>To frame miſchief by a Law.</hi> Now this odious Sin God hath taken ſpecial care to deterr Men from,
<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lavit.</hi> 25.14, 17</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall not oppreſs one another.</hi> The Quality of the Oppreſſed is an aggravation to the Sin, as to oppreſs the Afflicted,
<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.22.</note> 
               <hi>Rob not the poor, becauſe he is poor, neither oppreſs the afflicted in the gate:</hi> which inſtead of Comfort is to add Affliction to the Afflicted; ſo 'tis to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Widow and the Fatherleſs, which by name, as well as the Poor, the
<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.10.</note> Lord hath forbidden to do; among the ſeveral Characters which God gives of a wicked Man, this is one,
<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.12.</note> 
               <hi>he hath oppreſſed the poor and needy.</hi> God, who is a Juſt Judge, hath ſolemnly Declared that he will puniſh ſeveral ſorts of Sinners; Oppreſſors are among the black Liſt
<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>I will come near to you to judgment, and I will be a ſwift witneſs againſt the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172914:19"/>Sorcerers, the Adulterers, falſe Swearers, and againſt thoſe that oppreſs the hireling in his wages, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and the fatherleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Extortion</hi> is when Men lay hold upon the Straits and Neceſſities of others, to extort and ſqueeze out of them, more than they ought or can give; and in their urgent occaſions, to relieve them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hard and unreaſonable terms, as to lend Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney upon great and unconſcionable Intereſt, or elſe refuſe to do't, which is a Cruelty: Tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a wreſting by force, Threatnings or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that which is not his due, or more than it is; as when an Officer doth exact more than he ought, or than his Fees come to. I am afraid we had of late, and now have too many of theſe Unjuſt and Mercileſs Men: But let them know, that if the Law, in a way of puniſhment takes no notice of their Crime, at one time or other, God, if they continue and Repent not, will viſit them for it.</p>
            <p>Another kind of Injuſtice is called <hi>Illegal,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, or againſt Law, and this directly regards the Courts of Judicature: I confeſs 'tis ſad that Law and Equity do not always agree; and that ſometimes a Juſt and Conſcientious Judge, who, as in the Preſence of God, would diſcharge the Duty of his Place, is not always free in a Cauſe to follow the Dictates of his own Judgment, but muſt be drawn away with certain Formalities of the Law: thô in his mind he be ſatisfied a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Swears Falſly, yet he muſt Judge and Act according to <hi>Allegata &amp; Probata,</hi> and not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Judgment; but this being not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to our preſent purpoſe, I omit, and come to that which is.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:172914:20"/>
            <p>The Courts of Judicature are the Seat of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the Oracles and Interpreters of the Laws, which in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, are there Righted or Wronged. Thô I ſpeak not of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons but of Things, I gladly own that upon the Benches ſit ſome Perſons of known Abilities, and Integrity, yet that Profeſſion is not free from Flaws; it hath its Sins, and grievous ones too: is often a Remedy which proves worſe than the Diſeaſe; and for the Truth of this, I appeal to thoſe therein concern'd, that are ſincere, and make Conſcience of their ways, therefore Abuſes therein ſhould be Reformed, Things Regulated. and thoſe Springs when Corrupt, Purged: <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay Doing Juſtice,</hi> to <hi>Deny.</hi> and <hi>Pervert</hi> it, makes many times the Law to be a Grievance, and are Three abominable, thô different Degrees of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice. Long and tedious Proceedings at Law are Vexatious, Chargeable, and make one unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily loſe abundance of time; Why ſhould one put off till to Morrow that which he ought and can do to Day? May be, God will take away that Power and thy Life too; 'Tis an unhappy Inclination of ſome Men of Buſineſs, out of a Humour, Cuſtom, Pride. Neglect, Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of ſome other corrupt Motive or Deſign to prolong time to do things which require Speed: So that ſometimes it would be better to have to deal with a <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> who, before Men go out of his Sight, will decide a difference; and thô ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he doth one wrong, yet on the other ſide he doth a Kindneſs, with ſaying Charges, Time and Trouble: For what mean the Long, Tedious, and Chargeable Suits at Law, which become end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, to the ruin of Perſons and Families, and the Oppreſſion of the Poor by the Rich, who with ſtrength of Money, tire and diſable them from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172914:20"/>holding out, the Law, ſay ſome, is ever open to all, that is, for the Rich to Ruin the Poor; thus the Remedy is turn'd into Poiſon, which ever keeps things unſettled and at uncertainties, and affords continual occaſions for one to diſquiet and wrong another; and ſometimes both are ſerv'd like the two that Quarrel'd about an Oyſter they had found, one ſaying he had ſeen it firſt, the other, that he had taken it up; for he whom they referr'd the buſineſs to, did open and eat up the Oiſter, and gave each of them a Shell. The Emperor
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Tit.</hi> 16. <hi>de Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ temerè litiganti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Juſtinian</hi> appointed puniſhment againſt thoſe who went to Law without a juſt Cauſe.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Deny</hi> Juſtice when due and ſued for, is another degree of Injuſtice: We know a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent time to Examin and Inquire into the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, muſt be allowed; but after that, one may well expect to ſee it done: I cannot believe any Man in that ſtation can ſo far forget himſelf, as poſitively to ſay, I will not do you Juſtice, but not to do't is by a ſide-Wind in effect the ſame: Beſides the unneceſſary Trouble a Plaintiff's put to, and made to loſe his other Occaſions; <hi>bis dat qui citò dat</hi> is with me a good Rule; ſoon to do Juſtice or a Kindneſs lays a double Obligation. The Judge ſpoken of in the Parable, did not tell the Widow, You ſhall have no Juſtice from me, only
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>he would not for a while;</hi> at laſt he did, nor for Juſtice ſake, but out of a Selfiſh Motive, that is to be no longer troubled with her Importunities, and in the place, for this reaſon, our Saviour calls him
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>The unjuſt Judge.</hi> After he had paſſed this Sentence upon himſelf, <hi>That be feared not God, nor regarded Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to pervert Juſtice is the higheſt Degree of Injuſtice, as is to Condemn the Juſt, and Juſtifie the Wicked, which
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15.</note> 
               <hi>Both are abomination to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172914:21"/>the Lord.</hi> Or to give one that which belongs to another; this happeneth when out of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Heart, Judges, through Bribery, Favour, or other perverſe Motives, ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be byaſſed: when once any one hath been noted for it, he ought for ever to be brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Infamy, as being a Scandal to the Law, and a Shame to the Bench; the Injuſtices of Subordinate Judges cry loud for Vengeance to God the Supream Judge of all: Would to God there was not ſo much cauſe as there is to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of it; no Court, either Eccleſiaſtical, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick or Civil, is free from Abuſes and Sins, in relation to this laſt, I muſt give a hint of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abuſe, which is, When Lawyers undertake for Money to Patronize any Cauſe whatſoever, thô in their Judgment they be convinced it is bad: Indeed in dubious Cauſes, for a Fee they may make the beſt they can of it, but to encourage Clients in a wrong way, with telling they are in the Right, is certainly a Sin; for 'tis to betray the Truth, to engage them in an Ill Cauſe, put them to unneceſſary Charges, and Trouble, and make them run the hazard of being Caſt, and Loſers at the end.</p>
            <p>But a great piece of Injuſtice very common, and Hurtful is among Tradeſmen, who make a great part of the Nation: I do not ſay every one for ſome make Conſcience of their ways, but too many, when you come into their Shop, then out with their Lies; 'tis, ſay they, the beſt in the kind, coſt ſo much, and the like, to wheedle one to Buy, which the Apoſtle hath forewarned of and forbidden, when he ſaith,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>(Epheſ.</hi> 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away lying, ſpeak every Man truth with his neighbour.</hi> But the worſt is, that in ſuch Shops and Houſes are kept Falſe Weights, and Falſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172914:21"/>Meaſures, contrary to what God ſo often, and ſo ſtrictly Commanded his People:
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.36.</note> 
               <hi>Juſt Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances, Just Weights, a Juſt Ephah, and a Juſt Hin ſhall ye have.</hi> Elſewhere repeated,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.15.</note> 
               <hi>But tbou ſhalt have a Perfect and Juſt weight;</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and Juſt Meaſure ſhalt thou have.</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 20.23.</note> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary God abhorreth; <hi>For a falſe balance is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord, but a juſt weight is his delight.</hi> Again, <hi>Divers weights are an abomination unto the Lord, and a falſe balance is not good.</hi> Some have different Weights, one to Buy, another to Sell by. As to Meaſures, would to God there was leſs cauſe than we have to complain of it. I ſhall give an Inſtance which is obvious; and thô in ſome reſpect, the Thing be not of great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet the Sin is not the leſs; rather, becauſe it reaches many, chiefly the poor People, it is the greater. In many <hi>Alehouſes</hi> where an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man goeth for a Quart of Drink, out comes a Falſe Meaſure, a Black Pot, or the like, holding leſs than it ſhould; This for the Maſter, but the Drawer to have his ſhare, doth not fill it up but gives Froth inſtead of Drink; ſo that one hath at leaſt half a Pint wanting of his meaſure, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times but a whole Pint inſtead of a Quart; with ſome this Obſervation will ſeem mean: But for all that, I would have them to know that it is a great Sin, and no Sin may be call'd a mean Sin: And ſeeing I am upon this Subject, I far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall take notice of the Injuſtice of <hi>Brewers,</hi> who, for Inſtance, under pretence of a Shilling Excize given the Government, becauſe there is no Aſſize (which upon theſe Occaſions ſhould ever be to prevent Abuſes) they take, may be. Two for themſelves, and ſo make the Drink ſmall, raiſe the Price, and leſſen the Meaſure. The like may be ſaid of <hi>Bakers,</hi> who make their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172914:22"/>Bread Lighter than it ſhould be, or raiſe the Price of it. As <hi>Butchers</hi> do of their Meat. <hi>Chand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> of their Candles; ſo do other ſorts of Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, even as they pleaſe, without any curb put upon them; Thus the generality are left to the mercy of unreaſonable Men: And for they to plead <hi>The Liberty of the Subject,</hi> is an aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to pretend to, or deſire a Liberty to do wrong and injury. Here I ſpeak for the pooreſt ſort, who by ſuch dealings are the greateſt Sufferers. One of the chief grounds of Policy in matters of Government, is to Prevent or Remedy Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes put upon the People, about neceſſary Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Life; nothing more apt to cauſe Tumults and Inſurrections, than to want Food and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Money to buy it: One thing more I ſhall obſerve upon this Head, How in common Dealings, even without diſtinction of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Perſons, in their Bargains, according to their ſeveral ways, there is abundance of Falſe Dealing, Tricking, Cheating, and Over-reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and the worſt is, that when Men have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Point, they Laugh at it, and Brag of it; when the Tradeſman Sells his Commodities with Falſe Weights, and Falſe Meaſures, and not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with a moderate Gain, at unreaſonable Rates; Doth he wonder after, if he be ill paid, or not at all? thô I will neither excuſe nor ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the Buyer; but I ſay, 'tis Juſt with God to Retaliate him; ſo others are unjuſt to him, becauſe he hath been ſo to them. So our trivial Saving is very True, <hi>Honeſty is the beſt Policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are Sins alſo which attend the Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> as are ſometimes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Cure of their Patients, eſpecially when they are Rich, to have many Fees, and the more to ſqueeze Money out of their Purſe; and alſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172914:22"/>when they begin to recover ſtrength, to preſcribe ſtrong Remedies, to weaken them again. At other times they, without a due regard to the good of the Patient try Experiments upon them to the hazard of Life: And withal, thô no ſort of Men, more than they, have occaſion to obſerve the finger of God in the Works of Nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Power and Wiſdom are ſo evident; yet none more apt to attibute to Second Cauſes, that which is due to the Firſt and Supreme one: We know God hath appointed means to be uſed, and hath tied us to them, which we ought not to neglect, but Men muſt not be ſo unjuſt as to give them the Praiſe and Glory which belongs to God, who preſcribed, and whoſe Bleſſing made them effectual, for when God calls for our Life, all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies are in vain, <hi>Contra vim mortis non eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicamen in hortis.</hi> The recovery of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was not ſo much to be attributed to the Virtue of the
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>King.</hi> 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>Lump of dry Figs,</hi> thô the Remedy was very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the Diſeaſe, which was a Boil, and the dry Fig a great Drawer, as it was to God's Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, who, by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> appointed it. In this ſame predicament of Profeſſion we include Apothecaries, who to put off their Old Drugs, which having loſt their Virtue, can indeed ſtir Humours, but want ſtrength to carry them out, and ſo are rather Poiſon than Phyſick in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, keep the beſt, and thereby do Patients more harm than good; they ſometimes alſo leſſen the Doſe, yet will be paid for the whole: Beſides that, often their Bills are unreaſonable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and ſo a Sin in them. Under this Claſſis, for at the firſt, in the days of <hi>Hippocrates, Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides, Avicenna, Galenus, &amp;c.</hi> One and the ſame Man profeſſed Phyſick, <hi>Apothecarie,</hi> (if I may ſo call that Art) and Chirurgery: I leave for Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172914:23"/>to examine, and leave off Sins attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>'Tis a ſaying of <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that Sin, amidſt the Diſorders it hath cauſed in the World, hath left Mans Goods and Eſtates in the hands of <hi>Lawyers,</hi> his Body in that of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and his Soul to the Care of Divines: This is a great Charge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and thô every one be bound to look to his own Soul, yet God hath been pleaſed to appoint a ſort of Men, whoſe Office is to be Paſtors, Teachers, Overſeers, Watchmen, to Warn, Guide, and Direct others in the way to Salvation: The Care of Souls is a great and difficult Task, and a high Truſt, attended with a world of Lets, Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances, and Oppoſitions, from the Devil, the Fleſh, the World, and from Sin: Therefore without God's eſpecial Grace, which ſuch Men ought conſtantly to pray for, are liable to great and many Sins of the higheſt Conſequence; for ſometimes the Eternal Felicity or Miſery of Souls, doth, as to means, depend thereupon, and
<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Clergy,</hi> or Miniſters of the Goſpel, which uſe hath made to be the meaning of the Word, are called
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>and v.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Stewards of the Myſteries of God</hi> The Apoſtle in the ſame place ſaith, <hi>Moreover, 'tis required in Stewards, that a man be found faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> and blameleſs, for,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>A Biſhop,</hi> under which name is underſtood every Paſtour and Miniſter, as Overſeer of his Flock, <hi>muſt be blameleſs as the Steward of God, not ſelf willed, not ſoon Angry, not given to wine no ſtriker, not given to filthy lucre, but a lover of hoſpitality a lover of good Men, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, juſt, holy, temperate:</hi> The like charge to this is by another Apoſtle given the <hi>Elders,</hi> which is the ſame Office;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 9.1, 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172914:23"/>but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mind, neither as being lords over Gods heritage, but being examples to the flock;</hi> examples of Prety,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Charity, Temperance. Sobriety, Humility, and of every other Chriſtian and Moral Virtues, Learning of Chriſt, for
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>he is meek and lowly in heart,</hi> who
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 13.15.</note> 
               <hi>hath given an example</hi> or Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility: After the example of the Sovereign Lord and Maſter Miniſters ought alſo to follow that of the Apoſtles, as <hi>Paul</hi> gives himſelf for one
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>but be together followers of me, and mark them which walk ſo, as ye have us for an example.</hi> For his Deſign was
<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>to make himſelf an example un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others to follow him.</hi> Another Apoſtle exhorted thoſe whom he wrote to, in ſome particulars,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>to take the prophets who have ſpoken in the name of the lord for an example:</hi> I have a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for the high Character of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and of the Stewards of the Myſteries of God; and I know we have ſome who, as much as Human frailty can allow, perform the Duty of that Holy Office; but to others whoſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is too great, and who do not walk worthy of Chriſt, what <hi>Paul</hi> upon another account ſaith, upon this I ſay,
<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.28.</note> 
               <hi>I ſpare you;</hi> for the Offices ſake, I ſpare the Perſons unworthy of it, leaving them to examine themſelves by the Rules and Examples I mentioned a little before, Whether they have not prevaricated, but taken due care of Souls, fed them with the ſincere Milk of the Word, given good Counſel and good Examples, or a Scandal that made the weak of the Flock to ſtumble, and the enemies of God to Blaſpheme? I know, no perfection can be attained to, in this world, nothing without ſpots and ſtains,
<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 32.5.</note> but I doubt <hi>their ſpot is not the ſpot of God's children</hi> the corruption of the beſt things is the worſt of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172914:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:172914:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172914:25"/>all; and where more of Chriſt's Image in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, Purity, and of every Chriſtian Grace is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, the more conſpicuous, and odious are Sins and Things contrary to't.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>I fear,</hi> (to ſpeak ſomewhat like in <hi>Paul</hi>'s words) <hi>Leſt there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them debates, envyings, wraths, ſtrifes, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitings, whiſperings ſwellings, tumults, and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have not repented of the uncleanneſs,</hi> Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and other ſins, <hi>which they have committed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One fault more I ſhall but name, which ſome of the beſt are ſometimes guilty of, and that is In Preaching or Praying, to be inconſiderate (when in the Pulpit) in their Expreſſions, for they ſhould uſe none but ſuch as become the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the Great God, whoſe Ambaſſadors they are, and whoſe Holy Word they Preach, which ought to be done with an awful Reverence, and in a ſerious and grave manner; Graciouſly God allows them to be free in Preaching and Prayer, but not to be Saucy or Careleſs with him. There is beſides a worſe and greater Fault, and of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill conſequence, which out of Covetouſneſs they often commit, for to have Money, they in Priviledged places, as called, Favour Clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Marriages, and without examining about the Qualification of Perſons, Conſent of Parents, other Abuſes or Inconveniences, which to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent they ſhould be better informed and ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about, yet they Declare the Parties to be Husband and Wife.</p>
            <p>One of the greateſt Cauſes of Miſcarriages of Clergy-men, is the Ignorance and Inconſiderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Parents, who Devote their Sons to the Miniſtry, without inquiring whether they be well Inclined, Fit, and have the neceſſary Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications and Diſpoſitions for that Holy Office, which they look upon as a Trade, and to get a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172914:25"/>livelyhood, whereby is cauſed a great Prophanation of God's Service? In conſequence of this, a young Man doth not examine himſelf to know, whether he hath a Call to, and be Gifted for it; but when once he is engaged in't, doth indeed make a Trade of is, not ſo much minding the Duty, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the place, and is ſtriving from a Good to get into a Better Benefice; not to do good to the Souls of his Flock, but to have larger Profits, and more Income: Hence it is that ſometimes I have been aſhamed, and then moved with ſome Indignation, inſtead of good Pious and Profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſcourſe, when Three or Four Parſons are got together, to hear them talk after the rate of Farmers at Market, how ſuch a Benefice is worth ſo much, ſuch another more; one hath gotten a good one, and another hath a proſpect of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: For my part I could wiſh all Merchants and Changers of Money and Benefices, were driven out of God's Houſe, their Tables overthrown, and ſuch unſavoury Diſcourſes laid aſide, till there be a neceſſary occaſion, for they ſmell too much of <hi>Simony:</hi> Would to God there was no more than the Smell, but there's too much of the Body of it. And now I am upon this Point, I cannot forbear taking notice of a commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Care by a neighbour Nation, lately taken to revent <hi>Simony;</hi> by
<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>By the States of</hi> Holland <hi>and</hi> Weſt Fr. <hi>Dated</hi> Hague, April 18 1698.</note> a Proclamation, which thô it doth not concern us, yet the thing 'tis about, doth, and 'tis no harm nor diſparagement to learn good from others: Therefore out of it I ſhall take notice only of this, <hi>That-all, Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates for the Miniſtry in the Church, after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory Examination is over, when they are called to any Benefice to take care of Souls, ought upon Oath to Declare, that they have neither promiſed nor gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven any Gifts, nor cauſed to be given; nor directly or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172914:26"/>indirectly promiſed to any perſon for their being call'd; and know not that any hath done it in their behalf: The Controvenors thereof to loſe their places, and to pay Forfeiture amounting to four times as much as in Gift: Beſides the uſual Penalty inflicted for Perjury.</hi> This may work upon any that makes Conſcience of an Oath: But here the abuſe of <hi>Patronage</hi> is very great; the Preſentation, thô to take away the appearance of <hi>Simony,</hi> ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Tricks and Prerences are made uſe of, is ſometimes actually bargained for and bought; thus a Miniſter is intruded upon a Congregation who diſlike him, which is as bad as to force a Husband upon a Woman whether ſhe will or not.</p>
            <p>One thing more relating to the Clergy I ſhall obſerve, how to the grief of ſound and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Men, a due and neceſſary Care hath by ſome not been taken to curb and reſtrain the damnable Hereſies of <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> which of late have been and ſtill are too much abroad: I know, a late worthy Prelate, and others to their immortal Praiſe, have, as it becomes them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirred themſelves for this Cauſe; but in others there hath been a great Lukewarmneſs; I ſay not to Write, but to make uſe of the Authority which the Laws give them againſt ſuch things Beſides others, in the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 29. <hi>Caroli</hi> 2d. <hi>in</hi> 1677.</note> Act for taking away the Writ <hi>De haereticô comburendo,</hi> 'tis provided <hi>that nothing in that Act ſhall extend or be conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to take away or abridge the Juriſdiction of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Arch-Biſhops or Biſhops, or any other Judges of Eccleſiaſtical Courts, in Caſes of Atheiſme, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy or Hereſie, and other damnable Doctrine and Opinions, ſo that ſtill they may proſecute the Of fenders.</hi> This is ſtill in Force and Unrepealed, but certainly it hath not been made uſe of as it might and ought to have been. I am afraid that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172914:26"/>thoſe who in things of that nature have been ſo remiſs, would, if they had by the late Act, been allowed, have been more ſevere about Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Ceremonial things; for thô Thanks be to God, Perſecution about indifferent things be ceaſed; yet in many remains the perſecuting Spirit, and 'tis often found that thoſe who
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.24.</note> 
               <hi>Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a Camel will ſtrain at a Gnat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a great Mercy of God when he is pleaſed to raiſe up and ſend thoſe who give Men warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Danger, and of their Duty: Such are the fore-runners of a Bleſſing, as the Lord mentions it by a Prophet,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.6.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſet watchmen over thy walls O Jeruſalem, which ſhall never hold their peace day nor night.</hi> Theſe are the faithful Servants which never grow remiſs or weary, but are continually doing their Work, ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Guards, giving warning where there is any danger or approach of an Enemy; and how great muſt the Guilt be of thoſe, who when the Enemy is at the Gate, and the
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaia</hi> 56.10.</note> Wolves amidſt the Flock, are as unconcerned as <hi>Dumb dogs</hi> and <hi>Idol Shepherds:</hi> then in ſuch a caſe, even thoſe who are not Chriſt's Miniſters by way of Office, ought to ſpeak out; for which, out of that ſame place of the Prophet, they have God's Warrant, <hi>ye that make mention of the name of the Lord, keep not ſilence.</hi> When the Watchman doth not give warning, then any Member of the Society may give it for the Publick Good. And upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion this is my Warrant, and the ground of this Acting of mine.</p>
            <p>Another kind of Sins which the Nation abounds in, is call'd Sins of <hi>Age,</hi> for every part of Man's life hath ſome Sins, which that Age doth parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly incline him to. And Firſt, The Sins of Youth, as are Raſhneſs chiefly, Luſt and Pleaſures
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.17.</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:172914:27"/>of Sin, which heat of Blood in that Age draws them into: Theſe <hi>David</hi> could not forget, but Repented of,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.7.</note> and Prayed to God to forget and forgive, <hi>Remember not the ſins of my youth.</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, is one of the proper Sins of Men of ripe years, and Covetouſneſs, of Old Age; 'tis very ſtrange to ſee Men, the nearer they draw to the journey's end, the more ſollicitous to be to make proviſion for it, and God knows how many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful ways are by Men made uſe of to attain to their ends: The Nation is full of them; and thô we cannot tell all the Works of Darkneſs ſubſervient to their evil Deſigns, there is enough of it known to grieve the Heart, of all that love. God and hate Sin.</p>
            <p>There are alſo Sins of <hi>Relations,</hi> as are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Husband and Wife, how many daily miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages are there of one of thoſe Relations againſt the other? Want of Union, want of Love, full of Wranglings, Diviſions, Quarrels hard Uſage, and Abuſes, by one put upon the other: And no wonder, for God's Bleſſing go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not along with the breakers of ſo Sacred a Bond as is Marriage, of God's own immediate Inſtitution, at the very beginning of the World. There hath been a mutual Contract, a recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Agreement, a ſolemn Promiſe in the Preſence of God, and in the face of the Church; but is the Husband Faithful to his Wife? Is the Wife True to the Husband? Far from that, in too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Families, the Husband to maintain his Whore or to ſatisfie his Drunkenneſs, or ſome other Luſts, doth almoſt ſtarve his Wife and Children; and too often an ill Wife, to pleaſe her Vanity, and others, more than her Husband, inſtead of looking to her Family, and doing her ſelf and others ſome good, misſpends her precious time
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172914:27"/>with ſtanding idle before her Looking-Glaſs, Dreſſing, Patching, like <hi>Jezebel,</hi> Painting, and ſometimes in gaudy Cloaths, Gaming, Goſſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the like pernicious courſes, doth often Beggar her Husband. Thus
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>the Daughters of Zion were haughty, and walked with ſtretched out necks, and wanton eyes; walking and mincing as they went, and making a tinkling with their feet:</hi> But what doth God ſay to all this? <hi>Therefore the Lord will ſmite with a ſcab the crown of the head of the daughters of Zion, and the lord will diſcover their ſecret parts in that day; the Lord will take away the bravery of their tinkling ornaments, and their cauls, and their round tire like the Moon, the chains and the bracelets, and the mufflers, the bonnets, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of the legs, and the head bands and the tab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and the ear-rings and noſe-jewels, the change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſuits of apparel, and the mantles, and the pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and the crisping pins, the glaſſes, and the fine linnen, and the woods, and the vails; and it ſhall come to paſs, that inſtead of ſweet ſmell there ſhall be ſtink, and inſtead of a girdle there ſhall be a rent, and inſtead of a well ſet hair, baldneſi, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a ſtomacher, a girding of ſackcloth, and burning inſtead of beauty.</hi> Many of thoſe vanities our preſent times do not want, which they ſeem to have borrowed of them; ſo we may expect the like puniſhment. Some of theſe vanities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the days of the Apoſtles, therefore they would Reform it, and give the Sex the example of Holy Women in the Old times, <hi>for,</hi> ſaith he,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>after this manner in the old time; the hold women alſo who truſted in God, adorned themſelves, being in ſubjection unto their own husbands;</hi> and in the next verſe he names what old time he meaneth, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Abraham,</hi> for he adds, <hi>even as Sara obeyed Abraham calling him lord, whoſe daughters ye are as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172914:28"/>long as ye do well;</hi> and to inſtruct them well in this matter; he tells firſt Negatively, what this vain Apparel muſt not be, <hi>whoſe adorning let it be not that outward</hi> one
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>of plaiting the hair, and of wearing of gold, or of putting on of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel.</hi> Then Poſitively, what kind it ought to be
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>but let it be the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which is in the ſight of God of great price.</hi> But the more to confirm this Truth, another witneſs joyns with this.
<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>I Will—that women adorn themſelves in modeſt apparel, with ſhame fac'dneſs and ſobriety, not with broidered hair or gold, or pearl, or coſtly aray; but (which becometh women profeſſing godlineſs) with good works.</hi> All Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that have ſome regard to God's words, will mind this,</p>
            <p>Many ſins are committed in another kind of relation, between <hi>Parents and Children:</hi> often when Men want Children they deſire to have ſome, and when they have, they look, or ought to look upon't as a Bleſſing of God, for thereby they afford Church and State ſome Members; but do they afterwards anſwer God's end, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them Children? Do they take due care to breed them in the fear of God, and put them in a capacity to ſerve their Maker, and their Country? Sometimes they be very careful to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Eſtate for them, but not to qualifie them how to manage it well. If they have a ſine Horſe, they look out for a good and skilful Groom to Break and Order him, but often neglect the means to improve the Souls of their Children: What they do for them, is ſometimes not with judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and often it doth them more harm than good: They ought to give them good Counſel, and good Example, not to fright, but to entice
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172914:28"/>them to good things, bear with ſome Humane Frailties, eſpecially thoſe which attend the Age, but to make uſe of their Authority to curb and reſtrain them from evil things, ſhew themſelves enemies to every vitious courſe, as much as may be; infuſe into them a love for Piety, Virtue and Honour, with a Hatred to all that is contrary to't; they ought to ſtudy their Tempers and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, Reform what is Bad, and improve what is Good in them. When this foundation is laid, and there are in a Family ſeveral Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren 'tis Prudence in Parents not to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too partial for ſome, more than for others, for ſuch carriage hath cauſed great miſchief in ſome Families: Yet 'tis fit Parents ſhould ſhew their Approbation of thoſe Children that do well, and are virtuouſly inclined, and wiſely, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of thoſe whoſe Diſpoſitions are vicious,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>yet do not provoke them,</hi> but elſewhere I have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly written upon this Subject. Farther, 'tis the Duty of Parents, according to their Abilities and Quality to provide for Children, and diſpoſe of them in the World. This Scripture preſſeth upon them
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>The children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the Parents for the children:</hi> And
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>If any provide not for his own, and ſpecially for thoſe of his own houſe; he hath deny'd the faith, and is worſe than an infidel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide, How many Unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, Diſobedient, and Rebellious Children in the World? Some
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.3.</note> 
               <hi>are eſtranged from the womb, they go aſtray aſſoon as they be born:</hi> This is a moſt wicked and unnatural frame of Spirit, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred by all Nations, and by God's immediate Command the Offender was
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.20.</note> 
               <hi>puniſh'd with death.</hi> By a natural Right all Men are equal, but only in this caſe, there is by nature a ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172914:29"/>of one to another: Children ought to Love, Honour, Obey, and Help their Parents, But how many now a-days, who inſtead of being the Joy, Help, Comfort, and Support, are the cauſe of their Grief and of Trouble in many ways; and inſtead of a ſtaff in their Old Age, eſpecially to ſupport it, do rather ſerve to knock them down; but God will judge for ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now inſiſt upon the ſins here committed in another relation, between <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Servants:</hi> There are ſo many notorious examples, as any one may ſee them; on the Maſter's ſide are Hardneſs, Injuſtice, contrary to Scripture; not only Threatnings, which the Apoſtle exhorteth to forbear, but alſo Blows and Violence, not conſidering that
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>their maſter alſo is in heaven.</hi> On the other ſide, Servants are Unfaithful, Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, Vicious, Deſpiſers, when they are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>to be obedient to their maſters according to the fleſh,</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 56. <hi>and Coloſſ.</hi> 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>with fear and trembling in ſingleneſs of heart, as unto Chriſt, not with eye-ſervice, as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſers, but in ſingleneſs of heart as fearing God.</hi> And they ought to
<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>count their maſters worthy of all honour:</hi> 'Tis a common guilt with many Servants when their Maſters find fault with them, to Reply, which they are expreſly forbidden to do
<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>not anſwering again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Relation there is, between <hi>Rulers</hi> and the <hi>People,</hi> which hath its Sins great and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious: this being a ſlippery ſtep, one muſt be nice and wary upon't; howſoever it being of the higheſt concernment, muſt not go untouched: For ſuppoſe we ſhould ſpeak of the Throne, but with a due Reſpect; yet thoſe who Sit upon't, are but Men ſubject to like Infirmities with us. Humane Nature is in them attended with Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172914:29"/>and imperfections, for being Kings they ceaſe not to be Men: then ſometimes happen ſuch Conjunctures as Croſs, and are Lets in the way of the Government, which yet I ſay, not to excuſe thoſe who might do better, but only thoſe that cannot help it: Beſides that in all things we muſt obſerve a Governing and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Hand of God. 'Tis too uſual and common for Authority to mind its own Honour more than the Glory of God; and alſo, not
<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>to ſeek the honour that cometh from God only, but that which cometh from men:</hi> It was as truly as wiſely ſaid,
<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.8.</note> 
               <hi>A king that ſitteth in the throne of judgment, ſcattereth away all evil with his eyes;</hi> that is. ought to do ſo, and look upon Evil with a deſign to diſperſe it as the Sun doth the Clouds: Nay, 'tis ſin him Wiſdom to do ſo, theſe are the words of a Wiſe King, and not mine,
<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>A wiſe king ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth the wicked. and bringeth the wheel over them:</hi> 'tis not only his Duty, but his Intereſt ſo to do; for
<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.12.</note> 
               <hi>the throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſs:</hi> which he gives as a reaſon of what he ſaid in the beginning of the Verſe
<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.12.</note> 
               <hi>It is an abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to kings to commit wickedneſs;</hi> they ſhould mind Chriſt's Intereſt preferably before their own in this world, which in effect is to promote their own, if it be not contrary to the Lord's, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ought to begin,
<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mh</hi> 6.33.</note>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.13.</note> 
               <hi>Seek ye firſt the kingdom of God and his righteouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> After that, they muſt procure the good of their People, whom they ought to Love, and upon ſome occaſions, in imitation of God, <hi>to pity, as a father pitieth his children;</hi> the good Prince is like the true
<note place="margin">(q) 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3.26.</note> Mother of the Child, who had rather loſe her Right, than to ſee him torn and out in pieces. Tyrants are otherwiſe minded, <hi>divide &amp; impera,</hi> is their <hi>Motto.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:172914:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:172914:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:172914:31"/>again, Authority muſt be kept within lawful bounds, for in the world ought to be no unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Power, only God's: even giving juſt grounds of fear, ought in prudence to be avoided. Puniſh and Reward well thoſe who deſerve it, or elſe the neglect, or miſapplying theſe, can at laſt pull up by the root any Government, give thoſe who deſerve and want, and not undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Men to beſtow it upon their evil and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſes: It is a ſhame that Palaces ſhould be turned into a Den of Thieves, and be made a Sanctuary for ſome Brokers, Cheats, and the like, who there would ſhelter themſelves from the hands of Juſtice, whilſt other ſuch places as were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, have juſtly been taken away. Sollicitors of Pardons for Rapes are abominable, eſpecially when attended with ſuch circumſtances as highly aggravate the Crime: who without a juſt Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation can hear of it? No doubt for Money, or ſuch other Conſiderations, they will become Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates for Murtherers. Robbers, Sodomites, and Villains in any kind, God, who is the Supream Judge of all, hath committed ſome in High Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and theſe others under them, to execute Juſtice for him, in the World, and woe be to them if they neglect it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>People</hi> being a collective Body, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of ſo many different and contrary Humours 'tis not eaſy to ſpecifie all their Sins; only gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpeaking of the middle and lower ſort, in relation to Governments, when any way pinched, they are apt to fall in Diſcontents, Grumblings. Tumults, and the like, chiefly when they ſee themſelves wronged and oppreſſed, and finding no redreſs from the Government, they will make Reflections againſt it; for by reaſon of their yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Obedience, paying Taxes, and undergoing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172914:31"/>other Burthens, they think they have cauſe to expect Safety and Protection from Wrong and Injuries, but moſt of all when they want neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, either by reaſon of Scarcity, unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the Price, or want of Money to Buy: 'Tis the Prudence, and ought to be the Care of the Ruling Power, with removing the Cauſe, to prevent their doing themſelves Juſtice; for then they go beyond all Bounds, and ſo fall into Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Rage, Injuſtice and Cruelty, which hath given occaſion to the ſaying, <hi>a furore populi libera nos.</hi> Lord deliver us from the fury of the People; I know 'tis too uſual with them to repine at any thing that is amiſs, and to complain of the leaſt inconveniency, not conſidering that there happen ſometimes ſuch conjunctures and accidents, when miſcarriages are unavoidable, not ſo much through the fault of the Government as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence and contingency of Cauſes that have ill influences; as ſometimes we ſee a good Watch to be out of Order, not by any defect in the Workmanſhip, but by reaſon of the injury of the weather, or other accidents, which ariſeth not out of the Watch itſelf, and herein, and when ſuch things happen, I could wiſh the Government to pity thoſe whoſe ignorance of ſuch things make them uncapable of that neceſſary Obſervation, and deal with them accordingly. The Head muſt be the Seat of Wiſdom, but if it ſuffers Grievances to accumulate, and takes no care to prevent or redreſs with puniſhing the Guilty, and relieving the Sufferers, then not only the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant but alſo the Wiſe part of the Subject will ſuſpect ſome ill Deſign, wherof the bad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences are obvious; Fear is a great diſtemper in the Spirits of Men, which by all means State-Phyſicians ought without delay, go about to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172914:32"/>Cure, elſe that Diſtemper is of ſuch a nature, as can ſoon make it increaſe; wherefore when the Patient calls for Remedy, let it ſoon be applyed, or elſe there is danger, the Diſeaſe ſhall turn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Delirium and Madneſs, which ſome Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers are more apt than others to fall into, which ſhould make Rulers well to ſtudy how to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Conſtitution of the Government, and the Temper of their People. He who denies another a juſt thing, doth thereby provoke him to ask for things that are unjuſt, and if he hath ſtrength along with him, that will make him the more dangerous. Let <hi>Rehoboam</hi> be an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for all Rulers, who being influenced by evil Counſel, deny'd, and that in a ſmart way, to eaſe the People of unjuſt and heavy Burdens: 'Tis true, in that caſe 'tis expreſly ſaid,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.24.</note> 
               <hi>That thing was from the lord,</hi> ſo 'tis in every other, for ſometimes when Princes Rebel againſt God, in his Juſt Judgment, their Subjects Rebel againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Great Men,</hi> tho' placed in a higher Orb, yet come within the predicament of Subjects, and have Sins proper to their ſtation; ſome of them out of Pride, Ambition, or Covetouſneſs, make uſe of the Power which God hath put into their hands, to wrong and oppreſs their Inferiours, and conſider not their Authority, as means they are intruſted with to do much Good and not much Evil; for like Stewards they ſhall give God an account thereof; thoſe Abuſes of theirs are taken notice of in Scripture,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Do not rich men oppreſs you and draw you before the judgment ſeats? Do not they blaſpheme that worthy name by the which ye are called?</hi> If with Power God had given them Grace and Wiſdom, they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that their being Seated in High Places, lays them the more open to the eyes of others, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:172914:32"/>that their failings and falſe ſteps are more taken notice of, and expoſed to the cenſure of Men; they muſt not make Cyphers of themſelves, nor be like the fiery Vapours in the middle Region of the Air, which are taken notice of only by their fall; Great Men God hath placed within their Sphere, to give Light unto thoſe of an inferiour Orb, but too often they are conſpicuous only for their bad examples and the ill Influences they have upon others: They think themſelves to be above all Rules and <hi>Quod libet, licet,</hi> they may do what they pleaſe, which in them is a great miſtake; therefore often, God to make them know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, doth lay their Honour and Power in the Duſt, as of late years we have ſeen examples, even of Crowned Heads. That King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who hearing <hi>Alexander</hi> to be called the <hi>Great,</hi> ſaid, <hi>He is not Greater except he be better than I,</hi> he ſpake well.</p>
            <p>There are other ſins and of a very dangerous conſequence, the more becauſe ſo Epidemical, and theſe, committed by Men of ſeveral Sorts and Tempers; whereof ſome ſuffer their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be impoſed upon, others out of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, or for ſome Worldly Conſiderations, to their own Loſs, let their Heart to be Bribed in the choice they make of ſome Men whom they entruſt with their Concerns, who neither fear God nor love their Country, <hi>Atheiſts, Epicures,</hi> who oppoſe any thing that tends to promote Piety and Virtue, or to diſcourage Vice and Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who having ſold their Soul to the Devil to do his Drudgery; make no ſcruple to ſell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Men to do all their Will and Pleaſure: Therefore no wonder if Men ſo ill qualified, do for Self-Intereſt betray their Truſt: He who is not True to God will be Falſe to Man, thô in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172914:33"/>different ways; ſome above-board, others un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and indirectly; ſome by openly oppoſing their Friend's Intereſt, others with neglecting, withdrawing, and upon occaſion deſerting the Service, Theſe indeed are loud and crying ſins, which yet cannot excuſe the Folly of thoſe who Intruſted them with what's near and dear: As no Prudent Man will Truſt a Bloody Man with his Life, So none that is Wiſe, will lay his Eſtate in the hands of one who is needy and greedy: But the Sillineſs of ſome, and Diſhoneſty of others, do prepare matter for a Judgment to come.</p>
            <p>Thô I already have given ſome hints againſt <hi>Bribery,</hi> yet the matter is of too high a concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be lightly paſſed over; the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe now more than ever, like a mighty Stream it hath overflown all beyond bounds and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: One can neither look nor go any where, but 'tis to be ſeen and met with; it hath poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned our <hi>very Springs. Oh! the abominable wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</hi> Thus at firſt, the Devil, under a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pretence, blinded the underſtanding of our firſt Parents, corrupted their Heart, and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them to Rebellion againſt, and Diſobedience to their Maker. To go about Bribing Men, is to do the Devils work, and tempt them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit evil, to turn Rogues and Knaves, to betray their Judgment, Conſcience, Truth, Truſt, Good Name, Friends, Relations, Countrey, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ought to be near and dear, even God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as much as ever; for Money <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed his Lord and Maſter, and if they could, would deliver him too, and to Damn their own Souls. I would be for cutting off a Hand that offers a Bag of Gold, ſooner than that which takes it; for if there was no Giver there would be no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:172914:33"/>and none would be Tempted if there was no Tempter, who is the Devil's Tool: And to Tempt and Seduce is a damnable Office, which in Men argues a mean, a baſe, and a wretched Soul: A generous Spirit will ſcorn to take any advantage of the Frailty, Corruption, and Wants of another; or to lay Snares and a Stumbling-block before the Weak, which is ſo contrary to a Chriſtian Frame. This is not Policy but Knavery, for True Policy is grounded upon Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Honour, guided by Prudence, Wiſdom, and Experience; and through reaſonable means tend to good ends. Knavery is an effect of a dark Underſtanding, whereof Cheating, Trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Deceiving, with over-reaching, are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients. When any Perſon and Party are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſuch miſerable Shifts, which baniſh Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty out of the World, and makes way for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſerved, as they cauſe others to be, 'tis a clear ſign that they are at their Wits end, and deſpair of the Goodneſs and Succeſs of their Cauſe, ſeeing they would promote it by unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful means. Sometimes they would make ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pretences, and even God's Holy Name ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to their pernicious ends, who to them will ſay as formerly he did to his People, <hi>Thou haſt made me to ſerve with thy ſins, thou haſt wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me with thine Iniquities.</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.24.</note> And having for a while winked at, and ſuffered them to go on in their unworthy courſes of Bribing, Suborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Corrupting, Seducing, and taking Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Weakneſs, Blindneſs of Mind, or Falſeneſs of Heart of others, will at laſt ſend a blaſt upon all their contrivances, and as in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment overthrow what through ſinful means they had been building for bad ends, and to them ſay as be doth to the Sea,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job:</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou come
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172914:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:172914:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:172914:35"/>and no farther, and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtayed.</hi> And as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 5.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>he diſappointeth the devices of the crafty, and taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſs,</hi> may be, when they leaſt think on't; God, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all their great contrivances, will ſend Death with this Errand, come to give an account of thy ſelf. By what is ſaid againſt the Bribers, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to excuſe the Bribed in any ſtation or capacity whatſoever, no more than ſhall be thoſe who yield to the Devil's Temptations; for both Tempter and Tempted are guilty. It availed <hi>Adam</hi> nothing to caſt the fault upon another, that is, his Wife, nor <hi>Eve</hi> to ſay <hi>The Serpent beguiled me.</hi> For God paſſed Sentence of Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon all Three. Is it not a great Crime? Is it not a great folly in one to ſell his Soul for Money, or other worldly Advantage? Yet there are thoſe Men in the World, who to do an ill thing, will, aſſoon, and as often take a Bribe, as a Lawyer will take a Fee to ſpeak for a Client.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Beg</hi> is become a Trade full of Abuſes, which daily may be ſeen in the Streets: 'tis a Seminary of Idleneſs, Lewdneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I know ſome are fit Objects of Charity, but others uſe it as a Cloak to their evil Deſigns, which ought to be enquired into: Remember the Apoſtles Rule
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>That if any will not work,</hi> when he can, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould he eat:</hi> Here we have a parcel of Boys, known by the name of the <hi>Black Guard,</hi> who by a looſe manner of Life, inure themſelves to all kinds of Vice: So there are many young Girls who under the notion of Begging, are ſeen up and down the Streets, to drive on the Trade of Pick-Pockets, and Whoring: As to the Men, when they grow older they become wandring and ſturdy Beggars, and at laſt High-way Men, which if timely minded and remedied, might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:172914:35"/>and conſequently their being condemn'd to the Gallows.</p>
            <p>Here I cannot forbear taking notice of a thing, which thô, it may be, is not properly and in it ſelf a Sin, yet with Humble Submiſſion to thoſe whom it may concern, I ſay it may become a Sin in its Adjuncts and Conſequences, for it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords occaſion enough of Sin in thoſe unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Sermons, which our <hi>Boanerges</hi> do upon the <hi>Anniverſary</hi> Day, fulminate againſt the Dead and the Living, and thereby ſhew they know not what a Chriſtian Spirit is: This is too much like the Antichriſtian Practice of Popes, who every Year on a certain day, cauſe a <hi>Bull</hi> full of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be read. One would think that after Fifty years time, there ſhould be a Preſcription for ſuch things, and 'twould be well to forget and forgive that which keeps up Diviſions, and intails hatred and Revengefulneſs upon us and our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; as if of late we had not Breaches enough, but we muſt ſtill continue the old ones, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly keep an Anniverſary for the Aſhes of a Man; and with ſuch Religious Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as make the thing much the worſe, which upon another occaſion God grievouſly complain'd againſt, That
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.8.</note> 
               <hi>by ſetting man's threſhold by his threſholds, and their poſt by his poſts,</hi> they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned his Temple, and defiled his Worſhip, therefore he commanded them to <hi>put away the Carkaſſes of their kings far from him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 9.</note> whereby Men are ſtained with a kind of Idolatry, and a down-right Superſtition, a good and proper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, for this Caſe and theſe Times. A thing is ſometimes a Sin, and ſometimes a Puniſhment for Sin.
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed brethren,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>leſt there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God,:</hi> here to depart
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172914:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:172914:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:172914:37"/>is a Sin, in another place 'tis a Puniſhment
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.23.</note> 
               <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me ye that work iniquity:</hi> So the thing I now ſpeak about, may be both a Sin and a Pain for it.</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe Publick Sins, there are in the Nation <hi>Secret</hi> Sins, ſo called upon ſeveral Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, either becauſe they are the dear darling and boſom Sins in the Heart, ſo beloved, that the Sinner is content to part with God, with Chriſt, and with every thing elſe, rather than with them; ſuch <hi>Dalilas</hi> they cannot and will not leave, thô their Life lay at ſtake: O theſe prophane <hi>Eſaus,</hi> who
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.33.</note> 
               <hi>Sell their birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for pottage!</hi> O the Fools who prefer
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</note> before <hi>the fulneſs of joy in God's Preſence, and the pleaſures for evermore that are at his right hand!</hi> Elſe they be called <hi>Secret,</hi> becauſe committed in ſecret; for, Shame, which from the beginning of the World, as we ſee in our Firſt Parents, followed Sin, makes the Sinner hide himſelf as they did. Alſo they are called <hi>Secret,</hi> becauſe ſometimes the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders ſee them not, and are ignorant of, either by reaſon that they are too many, or elſe not minded, which made <hi>David</hi> pray for Pardon, and ſay,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12.</note> 
               <hi>Who can underſtand his error? Cleanſe thou me from ſecret faults:</hi> which ſometimes are above the reſt of ſo ſhameful a nature, as make the Apoſtle ſay,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>For it is a ſhame even to ſpeak of thoſe things which are done of them in ſecret.</hi> Theſe are <hi>the works of darkneſs,</hi> which he would have us <hi>to caſt off,</hi> and inſtead of them to
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>put on the Armour of light.</hi> Theſe muſt be left to God, and to the Conſcience of Sinners,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>until the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and will make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the counſels of the heart. For,</hi> ſaith Truth it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:172914:37"/>ſelf
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>Nothing is ſecret that ſhall not be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, neither any thing hid that ſhall not be known and come abroad.</hi> What Men have done in ſecret and in dark corners out of Man's ſight, God hath ſeen, and ſhall be publiſhed upon the Houſe tops, Some of theſe Sins appear and are great in God's Sight, for every Sin is the Tranſgreſſion of the Law of an Infinite, Eternal, and Almighty God, ſo upon that Account no Sin may be called Small, only comparatively; as there ſhall be degrees of Pains, ſo there are degrees of Sins which deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thoſe Pains: Yet theſe ſecret Sins are upon ſome Accounts, not ſo bad as preſumptuous and publick Sins, which cauſe God's Enemies to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, give ill examples, and ſtir up the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in Men's Hearts to do the like.</p>
            <p>Here are not only
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>Crimſon</hi> Sins of notorious Sinners, but alſo thoſe of them who ſtruggle againſt Sin, for God's People have their ſpots too, of many kinds,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.</note> for <hi>in many things we offend all,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46.</note> 
               <hi>there is no man that ſinneth not:</hi> 'Tis a Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Taught by the Light of Nature, for ſaith a Wiſe: Heathen <hi>Nemo ſine crimine vivit.</hi> But 'tis moſt proper to leave theſe to their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. Theſe Sins are fitter to be ſpoken of in a Pulpit, than here inſiſted upon: Beſides, they are not the crying ſins of the Nation; and thô ſometimes, God, like a Father, gently chaſtiſeth his Children for them.
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 30.11.</note> 
               <hi>I will correct thee in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and will not leave thee altogether unpuniſhed;</hi> yet never overthrows Nations, for the ſame, he gives them Repentance of, and they mourn fro them in ſecret.</p>
            <p>As there are ſins of Omiſſion, and thoſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable too, as well as of Commiſſion; ſo 'tis a Sin not only to commit any I named, as not to puniſh them; but alſo not to uſe means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:172914:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Sinners. 'Tis a Chriſtian Duty in a Friend in a proper and charitable manner, to warn his Brother, and endeavour to bring him off his Sin; but if that cannot do't, then other ways ought to be try'd, and one muſt go for help where it may be had. In another Caſe we have Directions which may be uſeful in this: When a Man who hath offended another, will not hear him, then he muſt take one or two more and go to him, but if he refuſes to hearken, then he is to go farther, and where is ſome Authority, and
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.</note> tell it unto the Church. Thus in this Caſe, if a Man doth Curſe, Swear, or in any other notorious way, break the Laws of God and of the Land, he that hears him is bound to go to the Magiſtrate, in whoſe hand lies the executive power, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form againſt ſuch a one. I know ſome preſently will cry our againſt an Informer, which indeed hath been a very odious Name, when gotten, for Unjuſt, Odious, and Unlawful things; as to take away a Man's Good Name, Fortune, Liberty or Life, to ſerve ill purpoſes, whether of private Men, or of a bad Government; but the Caſe is much otherwiſe, when the Honour and Service of God are concerned, which any wiſe to be inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to Defend and Aſſert, is in a Man very Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable: And becauſe the Magiſtrate, in whoſe Hand God hath put the Sword to be
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>an avenger, and to execute wrath upon him that doth evil,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be every where to ſee and know, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſtands in need of being informed, ſo there muſt be thoſe who can and will do't. Let the wicked World do what it can to revile, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule ſo good an Office; I will not mind what is againſt it, no more than the Experienced Pilot doth the roaring and tumbling of the Waves, or the croſs and ſide Winds, but ſtill
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:172914:38"/>ſteers towards his Point: As long as we have <hi>a ſure word of propheſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>we do well that we take heed as unto a light that ſhines in a dark place;</hi> Our Warrant for this is out of God's Word. and we muſt Obey God, and not fear Man,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt in any wiſe,</hi> or plainly, <hi>rebuke thy neighbour;</hi> the words in any wiſe go far, by all means, if you cannot directly: do't indirectly; if not of thy ſelf do't by others, if thou wanteſt Power, do't by thoſe that are in Authority; what is added is conſiderable, <hi>and not ſuffer ſin upon him.</hi> Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to get it removed, either by good and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Counſel, and if thoſe cannot ſerve, by Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. This is a Rule under the Goſpel, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as under the Law, repreſented as a moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Service, attended with a great Reward.
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 5 19, 20</note> 
               <hi>Brethren, if any one of you do err from the truth, and one converteth him, let him know that he which converteth the ſinner from the errour of his ways, ſhall ſave a Soul from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſins.</hi> Then 'tis a Chriſtian Duty in one's ſtation to uſe means to make a Sinner leave his ſins, if not out of Love yet out of Fear, which not to do, draws God's Cenſure upon the beſt of Men: The Son of God having highly commended the Angel of the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> for his Charity, Service, Faith, Patience and Works, yet finds fault with him, which is of the ſame nature with that we now are upon.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>Notwithſtanding I have a few things againſt thee,</hi> and what are theſe? <hi>Becauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman Jezebel to teach and to ſeduce my ſervants, to make them commit fornication, and to eat things ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed unto Idols.</hi> This Indulgence and Toleration of evil Practiſes and Doctrines, is condemned, ſo that no Man ought to ſuffer, but to the utmoſt of his Power, within his ſtation, to hinder with Accuſing, Condemning and Puniſhing publick ſins. He which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:172914:39"/>declares not Treaſonable Words and Deſigns, which he knows, deſerve's to be ſeverely puniſhed? So doth he who hearing Blaſphemy, Impiety, and Wickedneſs ſpoken, and committed againſt God, conceals it, which is no ſmall Guilt: 'Tis a kind of Rebellion againſt the moſt High, Eternal and Almighty God, and Treaſon in the Higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; therefore every Pious Man, for all the talk and frowns of the World, is in his capacity, but without ſelf-ends, bound to appear, either as a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to convince, or a Judge to Condemn; and upon this account God ſaith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 51.7.</note> 
               <hi>Fear ye not the reproach of men, neither be ye afraid of their revilings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Sin very common I muſt not forget, 'tis <hi>Want of Charity,</hi> which thô expreſſed in Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive terms, yet contains a poſitive Evil in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, for it uſually ariſes out of a principle of Envy and Malice, or at leaſt of Imprudence; when ſome Men wreſt, and give a miſconſtruction to the Words and Actions of others, and like Spiders turn all into poiſon: they take pleaſure to hear their Neighbour ill ſpoken of and ſlander'd, which they promote and encourage. <hi>Love</hi> or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which in <hi>Greek,</hi> the Language of the New Teſtament, is one and the ſame, is the fulfilling of the Law, for,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>He that loveth another hath fulfilled the Law,</hi> ſo the want of it is the breach of the whole Law, which is by our Saviour reduced to theſe two Heads, to love God with all our Heart, with all our Soul, and with all our Mind, and our Neighbour as our ſelves: Now if we do not perform this laſt, which cannot be when we are uncharitable to him, we will never do the firſt, for,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>He that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath nos ſeen:</hi> Charity is what God requires of us; for,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:172914:39"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>The end of the Commandment is Charity.</hi> And we are exhorted
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>above all things to put on Charity.</hi> which as another Apoſtle ſaith,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Shall cover a multitude of ſins.</hi> And without it every thing elſe is inſignificant,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Thô I have the gift of Prophecy, and underſtand all Myſteries, and all Knowledge, and thô I have all Faith— and have no Charity, I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> ſaith the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles:
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 3,</note> 
               <hi>And thô I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and give my body to be burned, and have no Charity, it profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me nothing</hi> Charity not only doth no evil, but alſo <hi>thinketh no evil.</hi> There are Men in the World who meaſure and judge of others by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo think evil of others, becauſe they do evil themſelves; ſuch ſhould remember what ſaith our Bleſſed Lord,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Judge not that ye be not judged, for with what judgment ye judge, ye ſhall be judged.</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4.</note> and <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another Man's ſervants? to his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth:</hi> The Advice which the <hi>Rabbies</hi> ſay <hi>Moſes</hi> gave the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at his coming down from the Mountain, before the reading of the Law to them, would in theſe uncharitable times be very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, be quick to hear, ſlow to ſpeak, ſlower to anger, and ſloweſt of all to judge.</p>
            <p>The Duty of every Chriſtian is, not haſtily to judge, or raſhly condemn one another, but rather out of a principle of promoting his Neighbour's good, friendly and gently in private to Adviſe and Admoniſh him, not with Authority, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially, which doth more harm than good, and commonly produces, rather a bad than a good Effect; but with a Chriſtian Prudence, by all means avoiding to expoſe his good Name: For if he be not tender of his good Name, 'tis in vain he will pretend to be his friend, or to do't for his good; and any one, thô indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:172914:40"/>clear-ſighted, ſhall eaſily perceive Malice, and ſome ill Deſign in the bottom of it: I ſay that gentle ways ought to be uſed, though the Party was in fault, and deſerved to be reproved for it, according to the Apoſtles Rule,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>Brethren, if a Man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual, reſtore ſuch an one in the Spirit of meekneſs, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy ſelf, leſt alſo thou be tempted.</hi> Thoſe Sons of Thunder who would bring down fire from Heaven and deſtroy all, know not what Spirit they are of, ſure I am 'tis not the Spirit of Chriſt. This muſt alſo be done in a fit and proper time; thus <hi>Abigail</hi> finding
<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25 36.</note> 
               <hi>Nabal in drink, told him nothing more or leſs of his folly againſt</hi> David, <hi>until the Morning light:</hi> 'Tis the Character of a good Man to be diſcreet in the management of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, either in relation to himſelf or neighbour.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.5.</note> 
               <hi>A good man will guide his Affairs with diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> He who cares not how he treads upon his Neighbour's Reputation, doth thereby diſcover Venom in the Heart, let his pretences be never ſo plauſible and ſpecious. In this World every Man hath Two general Parts to act, which thô in ſome things oppoſite, yet may well agree, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought under a due Subordination, and in relation to their reſpective Objects: I mean that of a Chriſtian, and of the Rank and Quality which God hath placed him in the World, and he may well ſatisfie both, and with Prudence perform his Duty to God, and what his ſtation requires of him: and as primarily he ought to mind the Glory of God, and Good of his Soul therein included; So Secondarily he ought to take care of his Honour in the World, when it croſſes neither Piety nor Virtue; and by all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful means defend it, when maliciouſly and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:172914:40"/>aſſaulted by bad Men. And this, thoſe that ſet themſelves for Cenſors of other Men's Actions, ought to take notice of, eſpecially when they know them to be no Deſpiſers of good Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when duly given.</p>
            <p>But the abominable Diſeaſe of <hi>Calumny</hi> being now ſo Epidemical, the danger of ſuffering it ſo viſible and great, and the harm thereby done ſo frequent, it requires the greater Care to prevent and ſuppreſs it: Nothing more deſtructive to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and nothing brings more confuſion into the World, than doth ſpeaking ill one of another: Whence do often ariſe Quarrels, Fightings, Duels, Bruiſes, Wounds, and Death, but from words Miſ-ſpoken, Miſ-reported, and Miſ-underſtood? O the Tongue that cannot be governed, thô
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>A little member, how great a matter a little fire kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth? it ſetteth on fire the courſe of nature.</hi> More miſchief proceeds from the Organ of Speech, than from all the other Members of the Body, as we may ſee in what the Apoſtle ſaith about it,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>With their tongues they have uſed deceit, the poiſon of aſps is under their lips, their mouth is full of curſing and bitterneſs.</hi> What in <hi>Engliſh</hi> we call Slanderers, or Falſe Accuſers, is in <hi>Greek</hi> called Devils, for the Devil is their Father; who as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>was a lyar and a murderer from the beginning.</hi> How many children in that kind hath he in the World,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.18.</note> thô in ſome different degrees and ways. But, <hi>He that hideth hatred with lying lips, and he that utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſlander is a fool.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some out of Malice, Revengefulneſs, or the like ſinful Principle, do either invent Lies with out any ground, againſt others, or miſinterpret their Words and Actions, and are glad of any pretence to Blacken their Neighbour with falſe Aſperſions and malicious Inſinuations. And theſe Men have another fortunder them, who publiſh
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:172914:41"/>the Lies and Slanders which the others forged, and ſo become <hi>partakers of other men's ſins:</hi> Both he who ſteals the Money, and he who puts it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Bag are guilty; ſo he who ſpreads abroad the Slander, is as guilty as he who invented it; thô herein ſometimes there is a difference, for ſome publiſh it out of Imprudence, others out of a ſinful Compliance, and others out of Malice, Nay, there are ſome, who out of their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Corruption, take pleaſure to hear others ill ſpoken of, and thô in their mind they be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the things are not true, yet in their Heart are glad of it; and contrary to the Rules of Charity and Prudence, will rather believe Evil than Good; thô in doubtful Caſes, the leaſt they ſhould do is to ſuſpend their Judgment, till they ſee a juſt cauſe, and not preſently to proclaim it abroad and thus fall into the ſnare, for this is a direct breach of the Ninth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neighbour;</hi> whether his Goods, Good Name, or Life be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. Spreading ill Reports upon uncertainties and hear-ſay, is a baſe thing, and odious before God, and a nice point in the ſight of Men, who being pinch'd in ſo ſenſible a part as Reputation, will kick againſt ſuch as thus laſh them behind: Neither do I think that the Laws of God and Men require in a Man the <hi>Stoician</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Inſenſibility, as if he was a Stock or a Stone, but rather do allow him in lawful ways, to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate his good Name, as to defend his Life. One Caſe excepted, when 'tis plainly for the Cauſe of the Lord Jeſus, then ſuffer all things gladly from thoſe that have Authority and Power over you: The <hi>Spaniards</hi> have a ſaying, <hi>Por tu honra pon la vida, y, pon los dos por tu Dios.</hi> Hazard thy Life for thy Honour, But venture both for thy God. 'Tis fit for the good of Human Society, that a ſtrong
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:172914:41"/>Curb ſhould be be put upon Authors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of Slanders' to take away from the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers all juſt cauſe from doing themſelves juſtice, when wronged in this caſe; and by theſe means ſhall Peace be kept, and it will ſtrike Terror up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Offenders in this kind; or elſe this will bring in Trouble and Confuſion: for there are ſome Men in the World who are as ready to venture all they have to vindicate their Reputation, when unjuſtly aſſaulted, as to defend their Life. This is ſpoken as to Men.</p>
            <p>But in relation to God, there are more preſſing Motives, not only againſt him who raiſes falſe Reports againſt another, but alſo againſt him that takes it up, Believes and Propagates it: God's word we have for it, for he that doth ſo, ſhall not abide in God's Tabernacle, nor dwell in his Holy Hill; for <hi>David</hi> puts the Queſtion to God,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, who ſhall abide,</hi> &amp;c. which he Anſwers, <hi>He that taketh not up a reproach againſt his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi> What is to take up a reproach? the Old Tranſlation hath it very plain, <hi>not to receive a falſe report againſt his neighbour,</hi> He who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be in God's Favour, and be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Houſe, muſt not hearken to, encourage or ſupport a falſe Report againſt another, but ſay, I will not be concern'd, and ſo let it fall. The meaning of the place is of a large extent; ſome explain the words takes not up a reproach, by <hi>doth not lift up ignominy</hi> and ſcandal upon his Tongue, and with it lays no ſnares to others, either with forming falſe things, or wreſting thoſe that be true: Who will not hear, ſpeak, or believe a Reproach or falſe Report againſt his Neighbour, thereby to keep innocent his Ear, Tongue and Heart. I ſay further, that in ſome caſes, Truth it ſelf, as to matters of Fact, when
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:172914:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>prejudicial to ſome body, ought not to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed without neceſſity, and a lawful Call, as when a Man is upon Oath, ſummoned to bear Evidence in a Court of Juſtice to preſerve a Man's Right; but when by ſuch Reports ſome body receives harm, and no body no good, thô they were True, ought to be ſuppreſſed and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: <hi>Doeg</hi>'s report to <hi>Saul</hi> of what had happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abimelech</hi> was True,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 53.</note> yet <hi>David</hi> for it <hi>curſed</hi> him; 'tis not always well and fit to ſpeak the Truth: A Son's Saying, <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a Thief and a Drunkard,</hi> may be True, but 'tis ill of him to ſay it; ſo 'tis, when againſt the Rules of Charity.</p>
            <p>Several other kinds of Sins we have here, which to mention would prove an endleſs Task, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, who can number them all? Whether of Inclination and Temper, of Relations, Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Conditions, Ages, of both Sexes, Family, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal and National Sins; and there is too much cauſe to complain, that <hi>England</hi> is become a ſink of evil in all ſorts, not only the iniquities of the Country, but alſo thoſe of others. How great Sinners from him that ſitteth upon the Throne to the Beggar upon the Dunghill, muſt we all be, ſince the Man, according to God's own Heart ſo heavily complained.
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.4.</note> 
               <hi>Mine iniquities are gone over mine head, as an heavy burden they are too heavy for me.</hi> And elſewhere,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.12.</note> 
               <hi>Innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evils have compaſſed me about, mine iniquities have taken hold upon me, ſo that I am not able to look up, they are more than the hairs of mine head, therefore mine heart faileth me.</hi> O that we could every one of us ſpeak of our Sins ſo feelingly and penitently, as He did of His; and that God would appoint over us Refiners and Purifiers; ſome <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> who alſo as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:172914:42"/>to Reign ſhewed their zeal for God, and againſt Sin.</p>
            <p>I hitherto have ſpoken of our Sins, I muſt now ſay ſomething of the puniſhment: With <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſay to my ſelf, and to all Sinners,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, God is not mocked, for whatſoever a Man ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that ſhall he alſo reap: For he that ſoweth to his fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reap corruption: But he that ſoweth to the ſpirit ſhall of the ſpirit reap everlaſting life.</hi> Here is Good and Evil, a Gracious Reward, and a juſt puniſhment offered, let us chuſe well 'Tis of God's Truth and Juſtice that Puniſhment ſhould follow Sin, he rewardeth both Good and Evil, we are told how
<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>every man ſhall receive his own reward,</hi> and ever it was ſo,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2.</note> for <hi>every tranſgreſſion and diſobedience received a juſt recompence of reward.</hi> There is a Reward for the Righteous, ſo ſaith our Saviour.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>Great is your reward in heaven.</hi> Long before, he had by <hi>David</hi> ſaid, that the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God's Laws was the way to't.
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>In the keeping of them there is a great reward;</hi> and as there is a recompenſe for the good, ſo there is for the wicked
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.8.</note> 
               <hi>With thine eyes ſhalt thou ſee and behold the reward of the wicked.</hi> We for our Sins have felt, and ſtill feel Judgments of ſeveral ſorts, for I muſt come home. Firſt, the <hi>Honour</hi> of the Nation is low in the world, which doth hit in a ſenſible part: Foreign Countries at this time want the Value and Eſteem which once they had for <hi>England.</hi> Time was, and 'tis not long ſince, when our Neighbours were in fear of, and had us in Reverence, but now 'tis otherwiſe, the reaſon is plain;
<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>Them that honour me I will honour. and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed;</hi> that is, ſhall be honoured by Men, as they are of God, as we have it in the examples of <hi>David</hi> at the latter end of his Life, of
<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro</hi> 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:172914:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:172914:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:172914:44"/>Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 32, 23, 27.</note> and their People under them, but now God hath ſmitten, us in that very tender part,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34.</note> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation, but ſin is a reproach to any people.</hi> Alſo
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Tribulation and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh upon every Soul of Man that doth evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtrength of the Nation is much weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, now it cannot do what formerly it could, and what remaineth of it, is through certain ways and means made uſeleſs. The Comlineſs is gone,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.11.</note> 
               <hi>For when thou with rebukes doſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect man for iniquity, thou makeſt his beauty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume away like a moth:</hi> For God is a conſuming fire, and we are as ſtubble before him: There is now a concurrence of Sins committed, of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted, and of others threatned, ſo that not only we feel, but alſo have cauſe to fear; for God's Mercies, we by our ſins, have made our ſelves unworthy of, and deſerved his moſt ſevere Judgments, We ſeem in our carriage aſhamed to Confeſs and Repent of our Sins, thô not to commit them; ſo that 'tis a wonder that having ſo often ſinned againſt Grace and the Goſpel, we have not quite ſinned it away, it threateneth to to leave us to go to others who will value it more than now many do among us.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Riches are leſſen'd, Poverty is come on apace upon many, I know thoſe who former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fared plentifully, now to want the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, even the Neceſſaries for Life: Trade once Flouriſhing, is now much decay'd, the Maſtery of the Sea queſtion'd, and a Blaſt laid almoſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every thing we undertake. We have felt the great Scourges, Plague, Fire, War, Unſeaſonable weather, one after another, and Dearth; yet are not returned to God; we are troubled with Partialities, Factions, Hatred, and Animoſities: The Nation is Divided, Subdivided, Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubdivided,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:172914:44"/>yet we will not return to God, but walk contrary to him; ſo no wonder if he walks contrary to us, and I am afraid it may at laſt be in <hi>fury.</hi> For as, we have been unthankful under Mercies, ſo we are become uncorrigible under Judgments; beſides, we have God's word for it, to be ſeriouſly read in the Texts
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>Joel</hi> 1. <hi>and</hi> 2. <hi>Amos 4</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.19, 20, 21, 22.</note> quoted in the Margin, which contain terrible Judgments, but the worſt are the Blindneſs of Mind, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart, which many are puniſh'd with, who mind not, and care not for the Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God's Providence, and are
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>Given up to vile Affections, and to a reprobate mind, to do thoſe things which are not convenient, being filled with all unrighteouſneſs, Fornication, Wickedneſs, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, Maliciouſneſs, full of Envy, Murther, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, Deceit, Malignity, Whiſperers, Backbiters, Haters of God, Deſpiteful, Proud, Boaſters, Invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Evil things, Diſobedient to Parents, without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Covenant-breakers, without natural Affection, Implacable, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmerciful;</hi> This is all now written for us as once it was for the <hi>Romans,</hi> for thoſe Sins are among us as they were among them, and I look upon them not only as Sins, but alſo as Puniſhment for Sins: For when God leaves Men to themſelves, from one Sin, they by his juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fall into another; for theſe Spiritual and Temporal Puniſhments are only Warning pieces; What then will the Murthering ones be? Do we wait and ſtay till ſome deſtroying Angel come upon us? Well may we cry out with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>It is of the Lord's mercies that we are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions fail not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read, how once upon an unſeaſonable weather of Rain and Thunder, in Wheat-Harveſt time,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>the people greatly feared,</hi> and cry'd out they had ſinned: And in another place 'tis ſaid, that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:172914:45"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>All the men of Judah and Benjamin trembled, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe of their ſin and for the great rain,</hi> which they look'd upon as a Puniſhment for it: So ſhould we, who of late, almoſt every Summer about Harveſt time, have had ſuch Rains as prejudiced the Corn, and other Fruits of the Earth, upon the like caſe as now ours is,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord's voice crieth unto the City,</hi> and Country too, and what doth the Lord ſay?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>hear ye the rod and who hath appointed it,</hi> and for what cauſe. There the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet makes an enumeration of ſeveral ſins, the ſame as now we are guilty of, namely, Treaſures of wickdneſs in the houſe of the wicked; Scant Meaſure, wicked Balance and Weights, Violence, Oppreſſion, a lying and deceitful Tongue; but mind the puniſhment:
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore will I make thee ſick in ſmiting thee, in making thee deſolate becauſe of thy ſins.</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">14, 15, 16.</note> And ſo proceedeth to the ſeveral kinds of ſenſible puniſhments which ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them. Theſe things were written for our inſtruction, that we might mend and be the better for it. Therefore before it be too late, let us hear the voice of the Rod, which ſaith, that according to God's Truth and Juſtice
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.17.</note> 
               <hi>Fools, becauſe of their tranſgreſſions, and becauſe of their iniquities are afflicted.</hi> Which in <hi>David's</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon's</hi> ſtile is the ſinner, this ought to ſtop our mouth, and the conſideration that we deſerve much more at the hand of God, removes all ground of complaint
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore doth a living man complain for the puniſhment of his ſins?</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God doth not in the leaſt proportion reward us according to our Sins, nor puniſh us after our Iniquities.</p>
            <p>The voice of God, and of the Rod are but one, (with this only difference, that one is of Precept, the other of Providence) and ſay the ſame thing,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:172914:45"/>how,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe of thoſe things cometh the wrath of God upon the children of diſobedience.</hi> That is, the things he named before, <hi>Fornication, uncleanneſs, covetouſneſs, filthineſs, fooliſh talking, jeſting;</hi> which with many more, are now the Sins of the Nation. The ſame voice ſaith to Whormongers, Thieves, Drunkards, and every other ſinner, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that God ſees thee, that thou muſt Die, yet knoweſt not the time when, then thou muſt
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>come to judgment before Chriſt, that every one may receive things done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> Then will God ſet all thy Sins
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21.</note> 
               <hi>in order before thine eyes,</hi> as it were in order of Battel to fight againſt thee. If Men would ſeriouſly mind this, and with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> ſay in Truth.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.8.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſet the lord always before me;</hi> and in whatſoever we do to eye him as preſent. I am perſuaded it might be a great preſervative to keep many from Offending. No Servant will willingly do before his Lord and Maſter that which he knows will diſpleaſe him: but hides from him as much as he can: but with God no Man can, he is every where, ſees, knows, and rewards all things, and when he puniſheth for Sin with <hi>Paul,</hi> we may ſay,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>We are ſure that the judgment of God is according to truth againſt them which commit ſuch things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when I am upon this puniſhment for Sin, before I proceed to another, I muſt out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bring ſuch examples of God's Judgments upon it, as ſhould make all Kings and People to tremble. <hi>Joaſh</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> I ſhall begin with: during the Life of <hi>Jehojadah</hi> he did well, but after <hi>the Princes made obeyſance to,</hi> courted and flattered <hi>the King who hearken'd unto them,</hi> and fell a ſinning againſt God, who to reclaim him and them
<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 24.17.</note> 
               <hi>Sent prophets to bring them again
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 19.</note>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:172914:46"/>unto the lord, but they would not give ear;</hi> and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one of them, which highly aggravated the Sins, and haſtened the Puniſhment
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>For at the end of that year the Army of the Syrians came againſt Judah and Jeruſalem, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all the Princes of the People, from a mongſt the People,</hi> who had been the evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors; and that which is remarkable, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered a very great Army into the hands of a handful of Men; for the <hi>Syrians</hi> were but few, and the reaſon is given
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe they had forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Lord, ſo they executed Judgment againſt Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 25</note> But this is not all, <hi>His own ſervants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt him, and killed him on his bed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abijah</hi> ſaid of <hi>Rehoboam</hi> his Father,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>That he was young,</hi> when he came to the Throne; yet 'tis recorded that he was
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>One and forty years old when he began to Reign.</hi> At that Age no Man may be call'd young; therefore 'tis to be underſtood, in relation to the ill management of his Concerns to the Succeſſion of the Kingdom over all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> wherein indeed he acted the part of a young Man. But I go farther, and find that
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>he did evil, becauſe he prepared not his heart to ſeek the Lord,</hi> ſo that he was a raw Man, no wiſer in matters of Religion than in thoſe of State, For 'tis farther ſaid in the beginning of that Chapter, that <hi>he forſook the law of the lord,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 1,2.</note> and all Iſrael with him,</hi> therefore God puniſh'd them, for <hi>Shiſhak</hi> came up againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> after he had taken the fenced Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and took away the Treaſure of the Lord's Houſe, and of the King's Houſe, and the reaſon was,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 15.29.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe they had tranſgreſſed againſt the lord.</hi> For in God's name a Prophet ſaid to them,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>Ye have forſaken me, and therefore alſo have I left you in the hand of Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhak.</hi> Here is a puniſhment for Sin, for <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>'s
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:172914:46"/>Idolatry, and his Son's and People's Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, whereby the Glory of the Kingdom alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy reduced within a narrow compaſs, was Eclypſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and its Riches carried away: Which yet was a lighter puniſhment than that which afterwards was inflicted upon <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> whom the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> took and bound him with Fetters, and carried him to <hi>Babylon.</hi> So that God ſpareth neither Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple nor Princes, nor Crown'd Heads, when pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by their Sins. This in theſe times we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pretend Ignorance of, therefore ought to take warning by.</p>
            <p>In the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the rending of the Ten Tribes, by reaſon of their Sins, nothing but deſtruction, and killing one another, this among themſelves; alſo God brought Foreigners among them, for he ſtirred up <hi>Tiglath-Pileſer</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> who took ſeveral places,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 15.29.</note> 
               <hi>and all the Land of Naphtali, and carried them captives to Aſſyria.</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.6.</note> And in the next Reign of <hi>Hoſhea</hi> who had killed his Predeceſſor <hi>Pekah,</hi> came up <hi>(r) Shalmaneſer,</hi> who carried away captive the Ten Tribes, and put an end to the kingdom of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And the Spirit of God hath left upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord the cauſe of it, namely their Sins, whereof in that Chapter is an enumeration from <hi>ver.</hi> 7. till the 19th. So of the Kingdom of <hi>Judah,</hi> when the meaſure of the Sins of their Kings,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.</note> and of the People was filled up, God ſent up <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> who took <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ruin'd and deſtroy'd the Temple, bound <hi>Zedekiah</hi> in Chains, killed his Children before him, put out his Eyes, and carry'd him with the People captive into <hi>Babylon:</hi> Wherefore this terrible Judgment? for their Sins, the King's <hi>Perjury</hi> named for one.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Moreover, all the chief of the prieſts and the people tranſgreſſed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much, and the Lord God of their fathers ſent to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:172914:47"/>them by his meſſengers riſing up betimes and ſending, becauſe he had compaſſion on his People: But they mocked the Meſſengers of God, and deſpiſed his words, and miſuſed his Prophets, until the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt his people, till there was no remedy.</hi> In many things this ſuits with our caſe, our Sins are many and great, if God move the Heart of ſome to ſpeak about it, we have too many of thoſe who will deſpiſe and ridicule them for it; Let us not hold out until God's Anger comes upon us, and till there be no remedy. O <hi>England,</hi> Rulers and People pray mind this before it be too late. I could upon this Head take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice how all ſignal Judgments in the World have been inflicted for Sin, which brought the Flood upon the firſt World, Fire and Brimſtone upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> utter deſtruction upon the Seven Nations in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which God, by <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to do.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord commanded his Servant Moſes to give you all the Land, and to deſtroy all the inhahitants of the land from before you.</hi> But time would fail me, if I would inſiſt upon all the Inſtances of God's Judgments for Sins, Recorded in Scripture. I pray God we be not made the next Example. For out of this we may ſee how God doth ſhoot his Warning-pieces, before he doth the Murthering ones. We have warnings enough, both at home and abroad; whence it comes nearer and nearer to us, but if we kick againſt the pricks, grow ſtiff-necked, and harden our hearts as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did his, then let us hear what God ſaith,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 20, 21, 22. &amp;c,</note> 
               <hi>But if ye walk contrary to me, and will not hearken unto me, I will bring ſeven times more plagues upon you, according to your ſins.</hi> Again, <hi>And if ye will not be Reformed by me by theſe things,</hi> that is, by the Plagues he threateneth them with, <hi>then I will yet
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:172914:47"/>puniſh you ſeven times more for your ſins.</hi> And in that Chapter the <hi>Seven times</hi> is often multiply'd, wherefore to avoid it, let us prepare our Heart to ſeek the Lord, or rather pray to God to do't for us; let us Repent, Mend our Lives, Reform our Manners, leave off our Sins, ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do good.
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 15.16.</note> 
               <hi>Man which drinketh ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity like water is abominable and filthy.</hi> Therefore compared to the <hi>Dog that returns to his vomit,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</note> and the Sow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then puniſhment is tied to the tail of Sin; and that in the Nation, we, thô in different degrees, are all Sinners, what elſe can we look but for puniſhment? According to God's Truth and Juſtice, Sins muſt either be Pardon'd or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, and is there no remedy for this? No other way to Pardon, but to Repent and Believe; or elſe nothing
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10, 27.</note> 
               <hi>But a certain fearful looking for, of judgment and fiery indignation, which ſhall devour the adverſaries</hi> of God. To make Puniſhment hold a proportion with Sins againſt an infinite Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. There can be no other way but Eternal Torments, beſides thoſe inflicted in this life: What Remedy have we for this? As we ſhewed the Diſtemper, Sin, and its due Reward, Puniſhment, for the wages of Sin is Death, whether natural, of Afflictions, Spiritual, or Eternal, we muſt now ſpeak of the Remedy: Be converted from Sin to God, and our Sins ſhall be forgiven. God hath appointed Repentance, conſiſting, <hi>Firſt</hi> In a contrition of Heart, or ſorrow for Sin. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> In a confeſſion of Mouth, or owning our Faults, thereby giving God the Glory; as upon the like occaſion did
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. from <hi>v.</hi> 5. to 20.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.5, 6, 7, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Ezra</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5, 6, 7, &amp;c. chiefly in <hi>Ch.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In a ſatisfaction given thoſe whom after God we have offended and wronged. And <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In taking, as far as we are able, a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:172914:48"/>full reſolution to forſake Sin, and follow after Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Righteouſneſs. Then when the Cauſe is removed, the Effect will ceaſe, and through God's Bleſſing the Remedy will produce a Cure of the Diſeaſe: Through a deep and Univerſal Repentance, <hi>Nineveh</hi> prevented the ruin which within 40 Days, ſhe was threatened with. Days of Faſting and Humiliation ſhould be kept, but not ſuch as God condemneth, as
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>a day for a man to afflict his Soul, to bow down his head as a bulruſh, and to ſpread ſackcloth and aſhes under him</hi> Such an outward and ſuperficial Faſt God hath not choſen, but <hi>to looſe the bonds of wickedneſs, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed go free. To deal thy bread to the hungry, to bring the poor caſt out, to thy houſe,</hi> &amp;c, Exerciſe Juſtice and Charity as well as Piety. This another Prophet call's to
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel</hi> 2.13. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.30.</note> 
               <hi>Rent your hearts and not your garments,</hi> God ſaith, <hi>Repent and turn from all your tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo iniquity ſhall not be your ruin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When once Men are really touched with a ſenſe of their Sins, and pricked in their Hearts, they, with the new Converts will ſay,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.</note> 
               <hi>men and brethren what ſhall we do?</hi> and with the Jaylor to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 16, 30.</note> Sirs, what muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> Long before a Prophet had anſwered a Queſtion about a Man's Duty:
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah.</hi> 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>He,</hi> God <hi>hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good, and what doth the lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly before thy God.</hi> To this anſwereth the Excellent Leſſon of the Grace of God,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.</note> by the Apoſtle mentioned firſt Negatively. <hi>Teaching us that denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts.</hi> Here we muſt begin, then <hi>we ſhould live ſoberly</hi> Here is our Duty to our ſelves, <hi>Righteouſly.</hi> This towards our Neighbour, and <hi>godly.</hi> This in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to God, <hi>In this preſent world.</hi> Which Three
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:172914:48"/>words contain the whole Duty of Man: So Men may not pretend ignorance of what we muſt know and do. This is every Man's Duty, thô of ſome more than of others, according to their ſtation, and every one ought to know't: Now
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47.</note> the ſervant which knew his lord's Will and did not according to't, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes, which to avoid, let every one with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſay,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.18.</note> 
               <hi>I will declare mine iniquity, I will be ſorry for my ſin.</hi> Not barely out of the Mouth, which ſometimes the moſt wicked can do: <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> ſaid,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſinned this time, the lord is righteous, and I and my people are wicked,</hi> So could <hi>Balaam</hi> to the Angel,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.34.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſinned.</hi> So <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.24.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſinned, becauſe I feared the people and obeyed their voice.</hi> Let all Princes have a care not to fear Men more than God. So ſaid <hi>Judas.</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.4.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſinned in that I have betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the innocent Blood.</hi> This Confeſſion of Sin muſt not meerly come out of the mouth, but from the bottom of the Heart, with Grief and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, attended with a real and ſincere deſire here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, to do ſo no more, to be able to ſay with <hi>David
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.23.</note> I kept my ſelf from mine iniquity.</hi> If God was pleaſed to make us all ſenſible of our ſins, and ſend us to <hi>Peter</hi> for Counſel; the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.38.</note> 
               <hi>Repent:</hi> but that Counſel muſt be asked, to that effect by the Angel's direction, <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſent for him. And <hi>Paul</hi> when the voice from Heaven came to him, ſaid, <hi>Lord,
<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ch.</hi> 9.6.</note> what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> No other remedy for Sin but Repentance, and to make it acceptable, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the Bloud of Chriſt: But how can thoſe who impiouſly prophane it, as too many among us do, hope to have any benefit by it? chiefly thoſe who like the <hi>Jews,</hi> one day cry out
<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Marth.</hi> 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> and few days after, and few days after,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:172914:49"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.1.</note> 
               <hi>Crucific, Crucifie him;</hi> as the People of <hi>Lyſtra</hi> who to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 14.13, 19.</note> would have done Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> but ſoon after ſtoned him. To ſhew how apt on a ſudden, ſome Men are to change for the worſe; or rather to appear really to be contrary to what they were but ſeemingly before.</p>
            <p>The Trumpet, ſaith (And who knows but that this may be the laſt Sound.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>It is high time to awake out of ſleep-the night's far ſpent, the day is at hand; let us therefore caſt off the works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and let us put on the armour of light; let us walk honeſtly as in the day not in rioting and drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, not in chambering and wantonneſs, not in ſtrife and envying.</hi> If not, I boldly denounce God's Judgments againſt impenitent Sinners, not as of my ſelf,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.21.</note> but after the Royal Prophet: <hi>God ſhall wound the head of his enemies, and the hairy ſcalp of ſuch a one as goeth on ſtill in his treſpaſſes.</hi> Wounds in the Head thô not Mortal, are known to be dangerous. We have daily examples of ſome who die ſuddenly, and of an unuſual death, there being in God's Quiver ſuch a number and variety of deadly Arrows: And will Sinners take no warning? Then in the name of the juſt God of Truth, I declare that thoſe who die by means of extraordinary Accidents, are not always great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sinners than we who are left behind, no more then were the
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Galileans, whoſe Bloud Pilate had mingled with their ſacrifices,</hi> or <hi>thoſe upon whom the tower of Siloam fell, and ſlew them, above all that dwelt in Jeruſalem. I tell you nay, but except we repent we ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> Time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent allowed us is a mercy, if we have the Grace to conſider it, or elſe the ſlower vengeance is a coming on, the harder it will ſtrike: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Men muſt not be afraid or aſhamed to ſpeak for God's Cauſe; for ſuch was <hi>Elias,</hi> ſuch <hi>John
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:172914:49"/>Baptiſt,</hi> and 'tis ſaid of <hi>Apollos,</hi> that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 18.25.</note> 
               <hi>he was fervent in the Spirit;</hi> after ſuch examples, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any pretence to immediate Inſpirations, only according to the rule of the revealed Will of God. I think I may be more plain and free in deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's Meſſage, which tends to a ſpeedy and ſincere Reformation in Doctrines and Practices, in Head and Members, which when compared one with another, admit of a difference; but in relation to God are all equal, being conſider'd in themſelves, Every Man's Breath is in his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, ſome have Death in the Head, others in the Lungs, Bloud, Stomach, Bowels; therefore all equally concerned to prepare for it, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Task given them to do, before they die. I think no Man in Authority, if asked, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it to be his Duty to raiſe and erect Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the Honour and Service of God; but he who hath a mind to Build, muſt clear the ground, and remove all rubbiſh out of the way. The building of God's Houſe is an Honourable Work, committed chiefly to the care of Princes, but when they mind their own more then God's, they give him juſt ground of complaint, which is follow'd with his Judgment. 'Tis likely <hi>David</hi> had not kept that good Reſolution of his,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</note> of the good Orders he ſaid he would keep in his Houſe and Kingdom, with puniſhing, correcting, and rooting out Wickedneſs; encouraging and favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Piety, Virtue, and Godly Perſons; But he was ſenſible that he was to begin at home in his own Heart, therefore he ſaid, as all Princes, who as well as ordinary Men meet with Croſſes and Troubles ought to do;
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18.</note> 
               <hi>If I regard iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in my heart, the Lord will not hear me.</hi> In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of this he would not ſee or ſuffer wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men in his Preſence, which made him ſay,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:172914:50"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:172914:50"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:172914:51"/>from me all ye workers of iniquity;</hi> and there he gives this reaſon, <hi>for the lord hath heard the voice of my weeping,</hi> implying that he would not hear him if he continued to keep ſuch. This is an example for all Kings to follow, who often have wicked Men about their Perſons, who Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Flatter, and for Self-ends do what they can to pleaſe them; thus they inſinuate themſelves into their Hearts and Affections; Such conſider themſelves more than their Maſter, and what they do is to promote their Deſigns, which, as they ariſe out of an evil Principle, ſo they tend to a bad end. 'Tis the Duty and Intereſt of every Prince who hath ſuch Men about him, to remove them from his Preſence. If Rulers go about to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, they ought thoroughly to know the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and well apply the Remedy, or elſe like <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 13.4.</note> they ſhall prove <hi>Phyſicians of no value.</hi> Then they ought firſt to begin at home, and in their own Houſes; Hence may flow a National Reformation, whereof the neceſſity hath with the Method well been
<note n="(b)" place="margin">An Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Societies for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> demonſtrated: of late God hath been pleaſed to ſtirr up the Hearts of ſome, as much as within their ſtation they are able, to encourage Piety and Virtue, and get im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and Vice diſcouraged and puniſhed: And if the Superiour Powers were pleaſed to lend a helping hand, it might (through God's Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing be hoped, in ſome good degree to ſee it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually done. Indeed 'tis very ſad and a ſhame that notwithſtanding <hi>Preſentments</hi> of Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>Acts of Parliament,</hi> and King's <hi>Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> for want of a due execution, Heretical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Sinful Practices go on bare-faced, which ſhould convince Men of a neceſſity to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſuch Abuſes; and upon a good warrant I may ſay, that except we ſpeedily go upon a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Family, and National Reformation, God
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:172914:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>will work it for us with a witneſs: His word I have for it,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>And if ye will not be reformed by me by theſe things,</hi> the Judgments before-mention'd, <hi>but will walk contrary unto me, then will I alſo walk contrary unto you, and will puniſh you yet ſeven times for your ſins.</hi> That whole Chapter is to be read with great attention, for it contains a great number and variety of Judgments which God threateneth his People with, for their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Holy Law and Commandments, which concern not only them, but us alſo.
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>For whatſoever things were written afore-time, were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our Learning.</hi> With the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> we muſt ſay, <hi>A good underſtanding have all they that do his Commandments.</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.8.</note> Now <hi>God will ſpeak peace unto his People, and to his Saints, but let them not turn again to folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>what I ſaid, I ſpeak not without God's War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I know ſome hate the very name of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> and Laugh at it, but if thoſe who want it, as more or leſs every one doth, do not work it, then God for their neglect and contempt, will Laugh at them, as under the name of Wiſdom, his Eternal Son, Declares it;
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24, 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe I called and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand</hi> in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and in judgment, <hi>and no man regarded: But ye have ſet at nought all my counſel, and would none of my reproofs; I alſo will laugh at your calamity. I will mock when your fear cometh.</hi> For this very thing an averſion to be Reformed, God in another place threateneth to Reprove, and ſet before the wicked, (for ſuch are all that deſpiſe God's Word;) his Sins like ſo many Enemies, in order againſt him:
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16, 17.21.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing thou hateſt to be Reformed,</hi> as 'tis in the Old Tranſlation, <hi>and caſteſt my words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee, I will reprove thee and ſet them,</hi> thy Sins, <hi>in order before thine eyes.</hi> The word <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is alſo known in the New Teſtament, ſo that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:172914:52"/>he who hateth Name and Thing, muſt be an enemy to God's word, for there hath been
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>a time of Reformation,</hi> of Legal Ceremonies, or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ordinances, as the Apoſtle calls them: Much more ought there to be a time of <hi>Reformation</hi> from ſinful Practiſes, for the former were once commanded and appointed by God, but the laſt were ever forbidden, Beſides that, as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly Sin, ſo we muſt continually Repent. <hi>Let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt depart from iniquity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is in the work of Reformation as it was in rebuilding the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for we read (as a brand ſet upon ſome)
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>That the Nobles of the Tekoites, put not their necks to the work of their Lord,</hi> So the Great Men, the Rich and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty refuſe to lend a helping hand to repair the breaches in God's Church, and to ſet up and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Service, and Honour. And of others, the chief and greateſt Men, we read how not only they would not help, but oppoſed the work of God's Houſe, and cauſed
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>the work of the houſe of God at Jeruſalem to ceaſe.</hi> One
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballat</hi> or other do what they can to ſtop the Lord's work from going on, yet in ſpite of their Teeth it proceeds on, a Man's Eye cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, no more can it ſee water run through pipes under ground; for God hath his ſecret ways of Providence:
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>We know,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, that all things work together for good to them that love God: Pharaoh</hi>'s cruelty haſtened the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God's People, and 'tis obſerved that
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>the more they afflicted them, the more they multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and grew,</hi> and this was the ground of the ſaying among the <hi>Jews, when the burdens are increaſed, then Moſes is at hand,</hi> that is, to deliver: I wiſh it was here not ſo true as it is, that ſome who ſhould ſet the wheel of Reformation a going,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:172914:52"/>either directly or indirectly do what they can to clog and ſtop it: Thô ſome under hand, yet others in defiance, and with a high Hand, like ſo many <hi>Pharaohs,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey his voice?</hi> And let my ſins go. I know not the Lord, neither will I part with my Sins, nor with my Lying, Curſing, Swearing, Forſearing
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>who have ſaid with our tongue, we will prevail, our lips are our own, who is Lord over us;</hi> nor with their Pleaſures; but for the momentary Pleaſures of Sin in this Life, ſlight thoſe which are
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</note> 
               <hi>at God's right hand for evermore.</hi> Nor with their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, which to ſatisfie they care not how they oppreſs others. As 'twas in <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s days, ſo 'tis now, in many particulars a like great oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Poor by the Rich and Mighty, which as then, ſo now, it cauſes
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>a great cry of the people,</hi> who are forced to Mortgage, to Sell, and upon unreaſonable and unmerciful terms to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Money to pay Taxes, buy Bread, and to ſerve other neceſſary occaſions,</p>
            <p>Now I ſay that theſe and other wickedneſſes, are ſuch as when committed and not puniſh'd, draw God's heavieſt Judgment, upon a Land: And thoſe Men whoſe Duty, and in whoſe Power it is to ſuppreſs Sin, if they neglect it, become thereby acceſſary to, and guilty of Sins by others commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſhall for it anſwer to God; I think eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man hath Sins enough of his own to give an account for, without bringing upon himſelf the burden of thoſe of others: Indulgence gives an encouragement to Sin, and carries along with it a kind of a ſilent approbation, when I call Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence a not puniſhing, I think to call things by their right name; now this is a great aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for after the enumeration made by <hi>Paul</hi> of wickedneſſes in ſeveral kinds; he adds,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:172914:53"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32.</note> 
               <hi>not only do the ſame, but have pleaſure in them that do them:</hi> They are not content to commit it themſelves but approve it in others. I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there is a great guilt contracted upon us, for we now do our ſelves what before we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd in others, whom we have ſeen God's judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments executed upon; which ſhould make us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid or the like, therefore ſhould take contrary courſes Do but keep out Sin, and ye ſhall keep our Judgment: But that which moſt of all is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borninable, tis that we have ſuch preſumptuous ſinners as boaſt and glory in their own ſhame; may be they never read, or elſe have forgotten what God ſaith by the Prophet,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he underſtandeth and knoweth me: that I am the Lord, which exerciſe loving-kindneſs, judgment and righteouſneſs in the Earth; for in theſe things I delight ſaith the Lord,</hi> and not in Sin, which I abhor.</p>
            <p>Once there were great outcry's againſt the Sins of the late Reigns, and there was cauſe for it, as God's Judgments which are always juſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: But are we now better in the leaſt? On the contrary, we can obſerve thoſe ſame Sins to increaſe, and daily grow ſtronger and more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent upon us. Have any of the guilty, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders againſt God and the Country, been pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for their notorious Offences? How can the Effect ceaſe, if we remove not the Cauſe, and what ſignifies to find fault, except we mend? I look upon't only as an aggravation: We know, yet act not according to knowledge, neither do we improve the means and opportunities which God had put into our hands, to aſſert his Honour and his Truth, to reform Abuſes, redreſs Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, promote the good of the Nation, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, Evil, reſtrain Sin, puniſh Sinners, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:172914:53"/>with greparing our Hearts unto God, to fit our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for further Mercies. Rather with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing, as we do in our Sins, and through our unthankfulneſs, we provoke the Lord, and are in a way to draw his vengeance upon us. The moſt notorious Sins of the late Reigns were <hi>Whoredom</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi> taking other Mens Wives, and without Shame, living with them in the ſight of the Sun: Alſo downright and open <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yet ſuch were Prayed for, as our <hi>Religious</hi> Kings, and <hi>Defenders</hi> of the Faith; when they were, about deſtroying it. So was <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> in pretending to be <hi>Protestants,</hi> tho' actually <hi>Papiſts;</hi> yet 'twas made Treaſon to ſay the King was a Papiſt, or Popiſhly affected; which I ſay, to ſhew how any Society or Aſſembly of Men, chiefly when guided by Intereſt and Paſſion, is apt to Err and be miſtaken; and thereby Men were made guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Death for telling the Truth. Well, theſe Sins and many more in Church and State, were under the late Reigns the cauſe of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and have been the grounds for our Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance: But what are we the better for it? Tho' God
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.50</note> 
               <hi>hath taken away</hi> ſome of the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nners, <hi>as he ſaw good,</hi> if the ſame Sins, in the ſame degree, nay in a higher, do ſtill continue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and are become our maſter Sins, is not there Cauſe to put this Queſtion, after God hath ſo graciouſly and wonderfully wrought for us, are theſe Diſtempers remedied, and all the great Abuſes we complained of, Reform'd, nay are we ſo much as in earneſt about to do it? Tho' we may ſay, ſome few are in a ſmall degree, yet far from it as to others; for, ſpecially thoſe relating to God' Honour and Service, are increaſed, and without reſtraint daily multiplied. We have bad Examples whence we expected good ones. How
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:172914:54"/>careful are Men to promote their worldly ſelfiſh Intereſt, and how neglectful of God's, as if it was not worth minding? Hence it is that we ſee obſcene, blaſphemous and impious Books publickly expoſed to Sale in Shops, Auctions <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without any Curb; and when there hath been other Books in oppoſition to thoſe; how much unfaithfulneſs, tricking and unfair dealings have been uſed to ſmother or mangle them about the time of the coming out; nay after that, for Love nor Money one could not get them put into the Gazzetts, among the Advertiſements, tho' deſir'd more than once. So that <hi>Diana</hi>'s Intereſt wants no <hi>Demetrius</hi> of ſeveral kinds among us.</p>
            <p>Some think they may be of no Religion, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of any, and profeſs what they pleaſe; ſome do vent and publiſh their Opinions, whilſt others cheat and revile their Neighbours, and wrong them in their good Name, Fortune, Liberty, and ſometimes in their Life, without little or no Curb at all, which is a bringing in a-pace of Confuſion and Anarchy; and all this, ſome would call the Liberty of the Subject, which is with Impunity to abuſe one another, and to run into all manner of Licentiouſneſs: Some think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Priviledged to Defraud others of their own, nay others go further to Strike thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe Character ought to be Reſpected, and that in ſuch Places as require a ſpecial Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and upon ſuch occaſions as deſerve Thanks and not Blows: Thus in one kind or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 17.6.</note> 
               <hi>Every one doth that which is Right in his own Eyes,</hi> as we read it was <hi>when there was no King in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus God in his wiſe Providence ſuffereth A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes to Creep in, and ſometimes to Prevail (of which we may ſay, what our Bleſſed Saviour
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:172914:54"/>ſpeaks of Offences,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>It is impoſſible but that Offences will come; but Wo unto him through whom they come;</hi> (by Right it ſhould be ſo with thoſe who commit Abuſes.) but alſo, he from time to time raiſeth Inſtruments in his hand for his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's good; and makes them as <hi>Paul</hi> would have us to be,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.16.</note> 
               <hi>Fervent in Spirit, Serving the Lord.</hi> As we read how his Spirit was ſtirred in him in <hi>Athens,</hi> when he ſaw the City wholly given to Idolatry. Not Lukewarm in his Service, for ſuch
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>He ſpeweth out of his Mouth.</hi> Nor ſuch as
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.10.</note> 
               <hi>Do his Work deceitfully:</hi> For ſuch are <hi>Curſed:</hi> But for his Honour and the benefit of his People, he makes uſe of ſuch as Love, Fear, and Serve him with their Heart; ſuch a one was <hi>Moſes</hi> to deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> to bring them into the promiſed Land: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity, God choſe <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel</hi> to carry them home, <hi>Ezra</hi> to reform their Manners, ſettle Religion, and build the Temple, then <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to build up the Walls of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> So he never wants Inſtruments to do his Work, and if ſome Men ly as Blocks in his way, he knows well how to Remove them: Happy thoſe whom he is pleaſed to make uſe of for ſo good a Work: But as Rules back'd with Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, make a greater impreſſion, ſo I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome, whom Scripture hath propoſed as Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns in matters of Religion, for after Ages to follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſa,</hi> I begin with; for after the falling off of the Ten Tribes, he was the firſt Reformer of the Kings of <hi>Judah:</hi> To his commendation 'tis Recorded of him that
<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.11.14.</note> 
               <hi>He did that which was Right in the Eyes of the Lord, as did David his Father, and that his Heart was perfect with the Lord all his days.</hi> Whereof Inſtances are given
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:172914:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:172914:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:172914:56"/>to ſhew how he minded the true Worſhip of God, and removed Abuſes therein Committed. 'Tis with every collective Body, whether Eccleſiaſtical, Civil or Politick, as with the Natural; in this, ill humours and deſtructive are ſometimes Bred and Formed, which 'tis neceſſary to Purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: Thus often Corruptions which cauſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, do creep into the ſore-named Bodies, which, to preſerve the whole, ought to be taken away and Remedied. This good King began his Reign with minding things of Religion; 'tis juſt that God ſhould be ſerved firſt: The Right way for a Prince to get nis Houſe Eſtabliſh'd, is to take care of God's; he is that good Maſter who provideth for thoſe Servants of his, who approve themſelves to be Faithful in his Service: But when they are more Solicitous for their own Concerns than for his, he then leaves them to ſhift for themſelves; but former and later Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſhew how ill they ſpeed that do ſo. Now let us ſee what that King did which was Right in the Eyes of the Lord:
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>He took away the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites out of the Land;</hi> that abominable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Sin, which God hath ſo highly declared againſt, he puniſhed; but ſtopped not there, he ſet himſelf againſt Idolatry too, for,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved all the Idols that his Father had made,</hi> and went farther, for he ſpared not his Mother, <hi>and alſo Maachah his Mother, even her he Removed from being Queen, becauſe ſhe had made an Idol in a Grove; and Aſa deſtroy'd her Idol and burnt it by the Brook Kidron.</hi> No Relation nor Quality ſhould be regarded, when it cauſes the Diſhonour of God through Idolatry, Blaſphemy or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. 'Tis a great Brand put upon <hi>Rehoboam's</hi> Reign, and a high aggravation to his other Sins,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.24.</note> 
               <hi>There were alſo Sodomites in the Land, which to</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:172914:56"/>his praiſe, <hi>Aſa</hi> his Grandſon took away, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the Monuments of Idolatry; for
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 14.3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>He took away the Altars of the ſtrange Gods, and the high Places, and broke down the Images and cut down the Groves. Yet he went farther, for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Judah to ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers, and to do the Law and the Commandments: Alſo he took away out of all the Cities of Judah the high Places, and the Images.</hi> All this is by the Spirit of God called
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>that which was good and right in the Eyes of the Lord his God.</hi> Pious Kings not only ſerve God themſelves, but alſo take care to ſee their Subjects do ſo: And we find that when in <hi>Judah</hi> there was a good King, the People was alſo good, or at leaſt reſtrain'd from doing evil; ſo much were People influenced by Commands and Examples from the Throne. <hi>Aſa</hi> did not ſerve God in vain, but found the fruits and effects of his Zeal, for 'tis added,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore the Kingdom was quiet before him.</hi> Whereby 'tis declared that the Reſt and Quietneſs of Kingdoms depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aboliſhing Idolatry, ſetting up the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and ſuppreſſing all that is contrary to Piety; 'tis further ſaid of him,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>He had no Wars in thoſe Years becauſe the Lord had given him heſt:</hi> And by the Prophet <hi>Agariah.</hi> God told him and all <hi>fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ah</hi> the cauſe of it.
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is with you wouldſt you be with him: But if ye forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi> Thus the juſt and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God rewardeth thoſe Princes who make uſe of the Authority he hath given them, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Honour and Glory. This King went on further, for after a great Victory,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 9.10. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>He ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered all Judah and Benjamin, and they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Covenant to ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers, with all their Heart and with all their Soul; that whoſoever would not ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:172914:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:172914:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:172914:58"/>ſhould be put to death, whether ſmall or great, whether Man or Woman. Whereupon they took an Oath,</hi> for <hi>they ſware unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and all Judah rejoyced at the Oath, for they had Sworn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all their Hearts, and ſought him with their whole deſire, and he was found of them, and the Lord gave them Reſt round about:</hi> after great diſorders in matters of Religion; what a happy Union of King and People towards a bleſſed Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? O that we might Here ſee the like in Parliament, where the King meets with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their Repreſentatives. Here among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Sinners, we have execrable Sodomites and Idolaters, not only thoſe who adore Riches, Honours and Pleaſures, and in their hearts and practiſes make them their Gods, but alſo <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters,</hi> thoſe who adore a piece of Bread, as they do God, and are not minded, thô con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Divine Laws, and to thoſe of the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſa</hi>'s Son, <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> continued the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and carried it further on; for
<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22.46.</note> 
               <hi>The Remnant of the Sodomites which remained in the days of his Father Aſa, he took out of the Land:</hi> alſo
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 19.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>He took away the Groves out of the Land, and prepared his Heart to ſeek God:</hi> Alſo <hi>He went out again thorough the People, from Beerſheba to Mount Ephraim, and brought them back unto the God of their Fathers:</hi> He not only would ſerve God, but alſo took great care that others ſhould do ſo; and 'tis written of him,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>He ſent Men to teach in the Cities of Judah:</hi> For he knew it to be in vain to profeſs Religion, except ſuch were appointed who would inſtruct the People in the ſame, and had power to remove all that is contrary to Piety, that is Men good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themſelves, and able to do others good. I
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:172914:58"/>wiſh all Princes would by the Example of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat</hi> take notice how plentifully God reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thoſe who ſerve him in Truth and Sincerity: Thus they might ſee how much it conſiſts even with their worldly Intereſt to perform their Duty towards God; this Character Scripture gives of him, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>He ſought the Lord God of his Father, and walked in his Commandments; therefore the Lord Eſtabliſhed the Kingdom in his hand, and all Judah brought to Jehoſhaphat Preſents, and he had Riches and Honour in abundance:</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>the fear of the Lord fell upon all the Kingdoms of the Lands that were round about Judah, ſo they made no War againſt Jehoſhaphat:</hi> The Reaſon is given, and 'tis this,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>And the Lord was with Jehoſhophat;</hi> and why was God with him? 'tis in the ſame Verſe, <hi>becauſe he walked in the Firſt ways of his Father David.</hi> So, is any Prince deſirous to be at Peace at home and abroad, to have Riches and Honour in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance? Let him like <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> walk in God's Commandments, promote his Service, and enlarge the Kingdom of Chriſt, who is King of kings, Lord of lords, and by whom Kings Reign.</p>
            <p>But as nothing is perfect in this World, ſo thoſe two Kings wanted not their flaws, for not to ſpeak fo their particular ones, as that of <hi>Aſa</hi> for relying on the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> for which <hi>Hanani</hi> reproved and ſaid to him,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 16.7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Herein thou haſt done fooliſhly, therefore from henceforth thou ſhalt have Wars</hi> as a Puniſhment, and alſo becauſe,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>In his Diſeaſe he ſought not to the Lord, but to the Phyſicians:</hi> That of <hi>Jehoſhophat</hi> was for
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.1.</note> 
               <hi>joyning Affinity with Ahab,</hi> and for helping him, which by a Prophet he was rebuked for, who went to meet the King, and ſaid to him,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:172914:59"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſhouldſt thou help the ungodly, and love them that hate the Lord?</hi> There was beſides a common fault in both, worſe than the others which were perſonal, and hindred not God's Work from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on; for thô they had done much for God's Service in the way of Reformation, yet they did not enough, not ſo much as they ought and might have done; for both their Reigns are branded with this,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.17.</note> 
               <hi>But the high Places were not taken away out of Iſrael.</hi> This as to <hi>Aſa;</hi> as to his Son,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.33.</note> 
               <hi>howbeit, the high Places were not taken away;</hi> which might partly be through want of a full Zeal in them, partly through the neglect of their Officers, and partly through the Superſtition of the People; becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>for as yet the People had not prepared their hearts unto the. God of their Fathers:</hi> However thoſe good Kings may not be deprived of a due commendation, for that only thing excepted, they went through the work of Reformation. O that we might but ſee here actually ſome Attempts and Steps towards it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> hath in Scripture the Character of a
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 32.32.</note> 
               <hi>good</hi> King: He began his Reign with taking care of Religion, for he reformed the great and many abuſes crept into't during the ſeveral bad Reigns, between <hi>Jehoſhophat</hi>'s and his. 'Tis ſaid,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 29.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>He did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, according to all that David his Father had done.</hi> 'Tis obſerved that <hi>he in the Firſt year of his Reign, in the Firſt Month,</hi> without delay, the Firſt thing he did, <hi>opened the Doors of the Houſe of the Lord and repaired them;</hi> which is a remarkable Example for all Princes; firſt of all to ſettle the true Religion, and to procure that God may be well ſerved. But this good King ſtopt not there, he reſtored the true Worſhip
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:172914:59"/>according to God's Inſtitution, Adviſed, Exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Commanded the <hi>Levites</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> to do their Duty about it: his own Diligence and giving good Example is mentioned, for 'tis ſaid,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>He roſe early and gathered the Rulers of the City, and went up to the Houſe of the Lord,</hi> and what they went upon, was heartily, cheerfully, and ſpeedily performed, for 'tis obſerved that
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 36.</note> 
               <hi>the thing was done ſuddenly;</hi> the Reaſon is given, For <hi>God had prepared the People.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at both <hi>King and People rejoiced.</hi> O that now Here God were pleaſed to prepare King's and People's hearts to ſeek unto and ſerve him.: But I fear all our Minds and Hearts are ſo crouded and affected with worldly thoughts and affections, that there is hardly room left for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly concerns, except out of his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, God be graciouſly pleaſed to make it. But let us hear what that pious and zealous King did; and I wiſh all Kings of the Earth, were like him: He went on further in the work of Reformation than his good Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors had done, for he removed all Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Idolatry, and every Idol of Jealouſie; even the high Places which others before him had not meddled with, for of him 'tis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded how
<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>he removed the high Places, and the Images, and cut down the Groves, and brake in pieces the brazen Serpent that Moſes had made; for unto thoſe days the Children of Iſrael did burn Incenſe to it, and he called it Nehuſhtan,</hi> that is a piece of Braſs, in contempt, becauſe it had been made a Tool of Idolatry; thô at firſt it had by God's immediate and ſpecial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand been erected in the Wilderneſs, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles had been wrought by it: This he did, and for this ſpecial Zeal of his in every thing,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:172914:60"/>obtained this Character, that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>after him, was none like him among all the Kings of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, nor any that were before him:</hi> And to ſhew that all this was acted in Sincerity and from his Heart, 'tis ſaid, <hi>he truſted in the Lord God of Iſrael</hi> and <hi>he clave unto the Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted not from following him, but kept his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi> He was not content to ſhew his zeal in <hi>Judah,</hi> within his Kingdom, but alſo invited others to do the like: To that purpoſe,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 30.1.</note> 
               <hi>He ſent Letters to all Iſrael and Judah, and wrote Letters alſo to Ephraim and Manaſſeh, that they ſhould come up to Jeruſalem to keep the Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over;</hi> which
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 18.24.</note> 
               <hi>many out of the other Tribes did.</hi> And the King, as alſo his Princes, gave the Congregation thouſands of Bullocks and Sheep; which liberality ſhews how Kings, Princes, and others whom God hath given means to, ought readily to beſtow it upon his Service, and to enable others to do the like: But to perfect what had been ſo well begun, for in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there muſt be no trimming, nor doing things only by halves; 'tis Recorded,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 31.1.</note> 
               <hi>Now when all this was finiſhed, all Iſrael that were preſent, went out to the Cities of Judah, and brake the Images in pieces, and cut down the Groves, and threw down the high Places out of all Judah and Benjamin, in Ephraim alſo and Manaſſeh, untill they had utterly deſtroyed them all.</hi> They began in <hi>Jeruſaiem,</hi> and followed all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try over. This Head I ſhall conclude with this remark, how God is graciouſly pleaſed, plentifully to reward not only in the World to come, but alſo in this, a ſincere zeal for his Honour and Service, as he did to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> for 'tis ſaid,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord was with him, and he proſpered whitherſoever he went forth.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:172914:60"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 32.27. 28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah had exceeding much Riches and Honour, and he made himſelf Treaſuries for Silver and for Gold, and for precious Stones, and for Spices, and for ſhields, and for all manner of pleaſant Jewels.</hi> &amp;c. Let all Men take notice how there are Rewards for thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote God's Intereſt; and within their Station procure others to do ſo, alſo Puniſhments for thoſe who do not.</p>
            <p>In the Perſon of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> we have a pattern of a compleat Reformer: There are ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary circumſtances relating to him, as make us look on him with admiration; for by
<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.1.2.</note> a Prophet, his Birth was foretold, his Name mentioned, and his zeal propheſied of, about 300 years before he was Born: Then he was but Eight years old when he began to Reign; and thoſe tender years of his, were in a high degree ſeaſoned with Grace, for then
<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.1. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>He began to ſeek the God of his Father David, and declined neither to the right hand nor to the left.</hi> Happy is the Country where ſuch Kings are Born and Reign, who aſſoon as they. Sit upon the Throne, take care of Religion, and to ſuppreſs Sin. The zeal of this good King, Scripture ſets forth as an example to others, to teach what God requireth of them: When he was but Sixteen years old, he ſhewed himſelf very zealous for the Glory of God, and when he was Twenty, he aboliſhed Idolatry, and reſtored true Religion in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and ſo continued to do in the
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note> Cities of <hi>Manaſſeh, Ephraim, Simeon and Naphtali,</hi> which belonged not to his Kingdom; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not truſt others to do't with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, this great Work, he would ſee it done with his own Eyes: For 'tis ſaid,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>They brake
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:172914:61"/>down the Altars of Baalim in his preſence, and the Images that were on high above them, he cut down, and the Groves, and the carved Images, and molten Images he broke in pieces, and made duſt of of them, and ſtrowed it upon the Graves of thoſe that had ſacrificed unto them.</hi> The Altar in <hi>Bethel</hi> which <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had built, and the high places he brake down, he defiled <hi>Tophet,</hi> put down the <hi>Chemarims</hi> or Idolatrous Prieſts, whom the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> had ordained to burn Incenſe in the high Places: He brake down the Houſes of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and ſo we may think he did of Baudy Houſes, if there were any, for he aimed at a general Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, whereof we
<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 <hi>King. Chap.</hi> 22. <hi>and</hi> 23.</note> read the particulars: How much grieved was he when he heard the Words of the Law, ſeeing he thereupon rent his Clothes! This his tenderneſs of heart, as of having humbled himſelf, the Lord took notice off by the mouth of
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.27.</note> 
               <hi>Huldah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſs. Now judge of the happineſs of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pious Kings, by the good effects and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences thereof, for not only they do good, but by their example influence others to do ſo: Often the good King makes his Subjects good, <hi>Regis ad exemplum,</hi> many times the People fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the King's Example; hence it is that in Scripture we read that when the Kings were good or bad, the Subjects were commonly ſuch as they, ſo like Prince like People, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 35.7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Joſiah gave to the People of the Flock, Lambs and Kids, all for the Paſſover-offerings, to the number of Thirty thouſand, and Three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Bullocks,</hi> and 'tis expreſſed, <hi>theſe were out of the King's Subſtance:</hi> So in the next verſe we read how that good example was follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>and his Princes gave willingly unto the People,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:172914:61"/>to the Prieſts and to the Levites:</hi> And to their immortal Praiſe, not only their gifts are ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but alſo the givers Names are upon Record: <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Princes were acted by the ſame Zeal, and they not only worſhipped God, but helped others to do ſo.</p>
            <p>Theſe examples are inſiſted upon, in hopes that at this preſent Time, and in this Conjuncture when Sins overflow, and there is a neceſſity of a ſpeedy Remedy, it will not be in vain: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any juſt exceptions be taken againſt what I ſay; for 'tis not I that ſpeak, but God; all is out of his holy Word. The Trumpet of <hi>Sion</hi> muſt Speak or Sound in the Language of <hi>Sion:</hi> Happy thoſe who can underſtand the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Canaan;</hi> 'tis a gracious promiſe as a Bleſſing to the Gentiles,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 19.18.</note> 
               <hi>In that day ſhall Five Cities in the Land of Egypt ſpeak the Language of Canaan and Swear to the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> I write as a Chriſtian, for Chriſtians about the things of Chriſt; therefore I lay aſide human Reaſon, Wiſdom, Conſiderations and Stile, to expreſs my ſelf in Chriſts, that is Scriptural Phraſe, to pleaſe God and not Men;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>for if I yet</hi> pleaſed Men, <hi>I ſhould not be the Servant of Chriſt:</hi> But my deſign is, if poſſible after
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.19.</note> God's Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, without diſtinction of Perſons to move Men to Emulation and Godly jealouſie to out-do one another; and upon this, as upon every other occaſion to practiſe the Apoſtles exhortation,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever ye do, do all to the Glory of God.</hi> Chiefly Rulers, who are publick Springs, whence the People draw, whoſe carriage the Subjects Eyes are fixed upon; and when the Princes heart is affected with zeal for God's Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, it commonly paſſeth upon and influenceth the People whoſe Head he is. Therefore he
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:172914:62"/>ſhould be careful of the way he leads them by, either into Salvation or Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>In the Chriſtian Church alſo, after many Perſecutions, Hereſies and wicked practiſes, God raiſed Inſtruments to do his Work, ſuppreſs Errors, defend his People, and purge his Church of notorious Vices. Such were the <hi>Conſtantines,</hi> the <hi>Theodoſius's,</hi> and other Chriſtian Emperors whom God made Nurſing Fathers to the Church: So in the laſt Age, at the beginning of, and ſince the Reformation from the abominations of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, ſome pious Princes in <hi>Germany,</hi> and other Northern Countreys, and in ſome Southerly parts of Europe, whoſe Names are to their high Commendation Recorded in Hiſtory: And here, Pious young King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. never to be mention'd without Elogy, who for Zeal in his tender years, might have been compared to <hi>Joſiah,</hi> if God had been pleaſed to have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him a longer Life; he upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons expreſſed his Piety and Abhorrency of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Idolatry; beſides that, Providence made this Conformity between thoſe Two good Kings, both died young, One by the Sword, the other (as ſtrongly ſuſpected) by Poiſon. <hi>Joſiah</hi> not long before the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Captivity: And <hi>Edward,</hi> juſt before the Judgment and violent Perſecution under Bloody Queen <hi>Mary,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Commonly ſuch matters as theſe, admit of neceſſary Cautions; thus when I was upon the point of Slander, (to which what I intend now to ſay, hath ſome affinity) I ſpake of ſome who under ſpecious pretences, as that they hate not the Perſon, but the Hypocriſie, or ſuch other thing which they invent, do put abuſes upon others, and thus to ſatisfie their Hatred, Malice,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:172914:62"/>Revengefulneſs, or ſome other diſordinate Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would bring in their falſe accuſations under the Name of the cauſe of God, and by theſe means impoſe upon imprudent and credulous Men, or eaſily perſwaded thoſe that are as ill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as themſelves, whom <hi>Solomon</hi> ſets this brand upon: <hi>A wicked doer gives heed to falſe lips,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>and a lyar gives ear to a naughty tongue,</hi> for <hi>ſimilis ſimili gaudet:</hi> Now in this place I muſt enter a <hi>Caveat</hi> which is this, That about the great Work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Life, Manners and other Abuſes, the Magiſtrates in the Execution of the Laws, muſt be very Cautious how they receive Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Informations from private Men againſt their Neighbour, ſpecially when the accuſed are for one quality or other Eminent above the Vulgar ſort; thus the Apoſtle charges his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>againſt an Elder receive not an Accuſation,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>but before two or three Witneſſes.</hi> They ought not to believe every thing they hear, but muſt firſt endeavour to know who the accuſer is, and whether he is biaſſed; for in ſuch Caſes, ſometimes,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.4.</note> (to ſpeak in the Apoſtles Words) <hi>falſe Brethren creep in privily to ſpie out</hi> occaſions of doing miſchief, and avenging their grudges and quarrels; ſelfiſh Men who would make God's Holy Name and Cauſe ſubſervient to their own ends: And if through their baſe way of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating, they gain their Point; they are pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, and applaud themſelves in't; and as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>they rejoice and are glad,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Habak</hi> 1.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they Sacrifice unto their Net, and burn Incenſe unto their Drag:</hi> And like the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> boaſt of the Miſchief which through the Credulouſneſs of others they have done; and ſay, <hi>by the ſtrength of my hand I have done it, and by my wiſdom, for I am prudent:</hi> Therefore when you are about ſuppreſſing one evil, have a great care not to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:172914:63"/>make way for another. Hot headed and fiery Men are not proper Inſtruments for the work of Reformation; they are fitter to Deſtroy than to Build up, and commonly they will uſe means not conducing to the true End. But the manner of doing things is that which Men ſhould be very Cautions in; 'tis not enough to do a good thing, but it muſt be well done, in a due manner, the ſaying is true,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Proſunt verba parum, proſunt adverbia multum.</l>
               <l>Non bona tam penſat, quam bene facta Deus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Will you get rid of Slanderers, then frown upon them, for <hi>an angry Countenance driveth away a back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting tongue,</hi> or elſe who can be ſafe? <hi>Si accuſare ſat eſt, quis erit innocens?</hi> A zeal for God's Glory is with ſome nothing but a pretence when it breaks the rules of Charity, without which no true Piety: 'Tis highly Commendable when ſincere and real, but withal it muſt not be inconſiderate, rather ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledge, and managed with meekneſs and Chriſtian prudence, for
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.23.</note> 
               <hi>the Servant of the Lord muſt be gentle to all Men.</hi> What ſuch Men call Zeal is only an Effect of the violence and imperuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of their Temper, and not a real deſire of God's Honour; 'tis more to pleaſe their paſſion than to ſerve God.
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 <hi>King</hi> 19.11.12, 13.</note> When God appeared to <hi>Elijah,</hi> he was not in the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>great and ſtrong Wind,</hi> nor in the <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> nor in the <hi>Fire,</hi> but in the <hi>ſtill ſmall Voice.</hi> God doth ſo when he comes in the way of Mercy; if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, 'tis in Judgment; and as God is Merciful &amp; Juſt, Men are commanded to be ſo one to another.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Peragit tranquilla poteſtas</l>
               <l>Quod violenta nequit.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Saith a <hi>Latin</hi> Poet; which is true, therefore gentle and fair means muſt be try'd before you come to hard and rough ones, for they effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally work upon ſome Tempers when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary do not: For this Reaſon I would have
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:172914:63"/>private Men that are willing to promote the work of Reformation, the more to gain upon the Spirits of Men, to make uſe only of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and leave the way of compulſion for the Magiſtrates, whoſe Office is to ſee the Laws ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted againſt hardned and refractory Offenders; but ever to avoid baſe and falſe ways. But when all is ſaid, Reformation is properly God's work, who turns the hearts, diſpoſes things and Perſons, and bleſſes means in order to't.</p>
            <p>But now to our Times, for we are more nearly concerned: The Nation is wholly overgrown with Sin in Soul and Body, we are quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with that Spiritual leproſie, ſo that with the Leper we may well cry out,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 13.45.</note> 
               <hi>unclean, unclean:</hi> And out of God's holy Word, the experience of all Ages, and of our own, with a witneſs we may know the ſad effects and conſequences of Sin, not only on the low Shrubs but alſo upon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Cedars. I can remember, (ſo may many more) how within this half <hi>Century,</hi> God's Thunderbolt hath, thô in ſome different degrees, lighted upon the Heads of ſeveral Countrys; I can name Six, nay Seven, whereof
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Charles I.</note> one loſt his life, and
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">James II.</note> his Son, his Kingdom,
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Frederic III. K. of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </note> another for a while loſt his Kingdom, and was a long time beſieged in his Capital City;
<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Chriſtina Q. of <hi>Sweden,</hi> died in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> Two others left their Crowns and Country, not ſo willingly as they would have had
<note n="(e)" place="bottom">John Caſimir K. of <hi>Poland,</hi> died Abbot of St. <hi>Germain</hi> in <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note> ſeemed to be, and went to Travel and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Foreign parts;
<note n="(f)" place="bottom">Alfonſo K. of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
               </note> a Sixth one, was Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported out of his Kingdom, confin'd in a Priſon and his Brother raiſed upon his Throne: All theſe were Chriſtians, thô of different Perſwaſions; the Seventh
<note n="(g)" place="bottom">Mahomet IV. the preſent <hi>Sultan's</hi> Father.</note> Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> Dethroned and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:172914:64"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:172914:64"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:172914:65"/>his Brother made his Succeſſor. God forbid I ſhould pretend to dive into God's Secrets, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the particular Cauſes of theſe Judgments; but I may boldly ſay, Sin was the general One; for except they had been Sinners, they ſhould have been no Sufferers; but let this make us all adore and tremble at thoſe Effects of God's wiſe and juſt Providence. The great
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.12.</note> 
               <hi>God is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to the Kings of the Earth,</hi> as well as to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men: When it ſeems good unto him, he can drive
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> from his Throne, and make his dwelling among the Beaſts of the Field, till he had humbled himſelf before him, for <hi>the moſt High Ruleth in the Kingdom of Men,</hi> and <hi>giveth it to whomſoever he will;</hi> herein the Pſalmiſt concurs with the Prophet when he ſaith,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.7.</note> 
               <hi>God is the Judge, he pulleth down one and ſetteth up another.</hi> He hath Angels whereof
<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.35.</note> 
               <hi>one can in one Night deſtroy an Hundred fourſcore and five thouſand Men of Sennacharib</hi>'s <hi>Army,</hi> and ſend him home to be killed by his Sons. The ſame God who then did, doth now Govern the World, and his Hand is not ſhortned, but that he can ſtill reach his Churches Enemies, yea, ſuch ones as in Cruelty and Falſneſs have outdone all the <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> and <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> in the World; and ſome wait to ſee what in God's due time, will be the end of ſuch <hi>Pharaohs</hi> and Oppreſſors as now are alive. When God chaſtiſeth Men, and his Arrows are faſt in them, they may and muſt own themſelves to be the Cauſe of it; and and with King <hi>David</hi> ſay,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.18.</note> 
               <hi>I will declare mine iniquity, and will be ſorry for my Sin.</hi> It were well to ſay and do ſo before the Judgment hath overtaken us; to prevent it therefore, bring forth Fruits worthy of Repentance: We know the Doom of the fig Tree that bare no fruit,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>cut it down, why cumbreth it the Ground?</hi> For Three
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:172914:65"/>years he had been looking for fruit, but found none. God hath been waiting for fruit from ſome of us, not only Three but Thirty years and more, yet we are barren ſtill; at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the dreſſer of the Vineyard, there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve granted for a year longer, <hi>lord let it alone this year alſo, till I ſhall dig about it and dung it, and if it bear not fruit, then after that thou ſhalt cut it down.</hi> As this is the Caſe of many a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Man, ſo it hath been, and is in general that of the World: Thus it happened with the firſt World, God for ſeveral years waited for fruit, but finding none, at laſt his patience being tired out, he brought the Flood upon them and thô they had been forewarned a Hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years before; yet, it took them unawares, for <hi>they were cating and drinking,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>marrying and giving in marriage,</hi> and <hi>knew not until the Flood came and took them all away:</hi> And juſt before the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Sodom,</hi> two Angels adviſed <hi>Lot</hi> to bring his Relations out of the Town, not to be invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in its Ruin: But when <hi>Lot</hi> ſpake unto his Sons in Law, they would take no warning, but <hi>Lot ſeemed as one that mocked unto his Sons in Law;</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.14.</note> but they were ſoon hurried away in that terrible Judgment. As for us doth not our Saviour ſay, that <hi>the coming of the Son of Man ſhall be as it was in the days of Noah,</hi> unexpectedly ſhall ſurpriſe this World, as the other was; for we are come to the Fourth year, the laſt of the tryal; the <hi>Firſt</hi> was from the Creation to the Flood, the <hi>Second</hi> from the Flood till <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Law, wherein <hi>Sodom, Gomorrah, Admah, Zeboim</hi> and all the Plains were overthrown, the <hi>Third</hi> year from <hi>Moſes</hi> or the Law, wherein the Seven Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were deſtroyed by the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> till the coming of Chriſt, the <hi>Fourth</hi> from his firſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:172914:66"/>to his ſecond coming, when utter Ruin ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall the impenitent and unbelievers; let all Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners mind this and tremble.</p>
            <p>And now O Sinner, I ſpeak without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Perſons; I will try, and then try rhy ſelf whether thou art one of thoſe who
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>after thy hardneſs and impenitent heart treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt up to thy ſelf wrath againſt the day of wrath, and revelation of the righteous Judgment of God:</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>thine underſtanding darkned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alienated from the life of God through the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that is in thee, becauſe of the blindneſs of thine heart, who being paſt feeling, hath given thy ſelf over unto laſciviouſneſs, to work all uncleanneſs?</hi> Or whether there be in thee any thing of good Nature, or rather of Grace, and ſomething left of humanity? This may be known if thou wilt be ſerious upon the meditation of <hi>the Love of</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt which paſſeth knowledge:</hi> Conſider well how out of the motive of that tree Love of his to thee and to me; he for a time parted with an infinite, unſpeakable and incomprehenſible Glory,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 17.5.</note> which he had in Heaven together with the Father, before the World was: Attended by Millions of Millions of Angels waiting for his Commands, and who
<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>dwelt in the Light which no Man can approach unto;</hi> all this he was content to leave, and
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>being in the Form of God, thought it not rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery to be equal with God, yet made himſelf of no Reputation, and took upon him the form of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; nay, became</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.6.</note> 
               <hi>a Worm and no Man,</hi> the reproach of Men, deſpiſed of the People. Our human Nature he took upon him with all her infirmities, only Sin excepted; for he was hungry, thirſty, weary, ſorrowful, and he wept. He often was
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Mark</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0 <hi>Luke</hi> 8.53.</note> 
               <hi>laughed to ſcorn, contemned</hi> and hated by Men, not for any fault of his, for he
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:172914:66"/>had none; but for thy Sins and mine, which were the <hi>Judas</hi> that betray'd him, the <hi>Jews</hi> that that accuſed, the <hi>Pilate</hi> that Condemn'd, and the <hi>Souldiers</hi> that Crucified him, the thorns which fetched Blood out of his Sacred Head, the nails that fixed him to the Croſs, pierced his Hands and Feet, and the Spear which pierced his Side. O Sinner, O wretched ſinner, O wicked and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable ſinner, I may ſay, canſt thou look upon Jeſus in his Agony, ſweating great drops of Blood, his Soul ſorrowful even unto death, and under ſuch circumſtances as was neceſſary for an Angel to come down from Heaven to comfort and ſtrengthen him; canſt thou ſee and be unconcerned at all this? Thou ſeeſt him upon the Croſs praying for thee leaning down his Head to Kiſs, and ſtretching out his Arms to Embrace thee, and ſhall not this work upon thine heart? He came down to ſave thee, and wilt thou damn thy ſelf? He came to deſtroy the work of the Devil, that is Sin, and wilt thou in thine heart and boſom receive, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, cheriſh and prefer before him that Enemy of his and of thine; ſo that thou hadſt rather part with Chriſt than with thy Sin. O ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious blindneſs and madneſs; by his Death and Paſſion he hath delivered thee from the Curſe of the Law, and of God's wrath to come, he hath ſubdued all thine Enemies, Death, the Grave and the Devil; for as Chriſt was viſibly Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſo <hi>Satan</hi> was inviſibly; he hath through his precious Blood reſcued thee from the Bondage and power of Sin; and wilt thou ſtill continue in it? Where is thy thankfulneſs to him who hath done and ſuffered ſo much for thee? If thou wilt not come to thy ſelf from thine heart to give him thanks and Honour, thou art as
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:172914:67"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:172914:67"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:172914:68"/>bad as the Devil, and worſe than all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for when he was upon the Croſs, the whole work of Creation was out of order, there was a great Earthquake, the Graves were open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the vail of the Temple was rent in the midſt, whole Nature put on a mourning Garment, the Sun was darkned, no light of the Moon or of the Stars, for <hi>there was a darkneſs over all the Earth,</hi> which made a Heathen ſay,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Apoll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Tya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus.</note> 
               <hi>aut Deus naturae patitur, aut Mundi Machina diſſolvitur.</hi> Either the God of Nature doth ſuffer, which was true, or this World is come to an end: And thou canſt look upon a bleeding <hi>Jeſus</hi> upon the Croſs, as unconcerned and with a heart harder than the very Rocks, which upon that occaſion rent: Then prepare for Hell as thine own home and proper place,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 31.3.</note> for <hi>deſtruction is to the wicked.</hi> One look of his upon <hi>Peter,</hi> having made him remember only one of his Sins, did work ſo much upon him, as that thereupon <hi>he went out and wept bitterly;</hi> the Centurion and they that were with him, when they ſaw the things that were done, <hi>feared greatly,</hi> and <hi>all the People that were come together to ſee that ſight, ſmote their Breaſt;</hi> and canſt thou be the only ſpectator of the Sufferings he underwent for thy Sins, and not ſhed for grief and ſorrow Tears of Repentance, and part with thy Sins? Then thou art a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Nature. Know that thou canſt not keep both Sin and Chriſt, Chriſt is in Heaven, where is no Sin; Sin ſhall for ever be in Hell, but Chriſt not, except it be in his Juſtice.</p>
            <p>But a thing which deſerves our whole atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thankfulneſs and admiration, and which adds an infinite value and merit to our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Actings and Sufferings is this, that they were the Actings and Sufferings, not of a meer
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:172914:68"/>Man but of a God, thô not of the Godhead. If he had been a bare Man, the obligation had been much inferiour to what it is; but the ſame Perſon was God as well as Man, which makes all Tranſcendently more precious than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it had been. God the Father did for our ſins deliver his only begotten to death, and that only Son voluntarily gave himſelf for us: O the exceeding riches of God's Grace in his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards us; The whole World can afford nothing to parallel with this; indeed the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> were Types of, but nothing to it; for what a compariſon can there be between Eternal, Almighty and infinite God, with a poor worm of the Earth, <hi>but duſt and aſhes,</hi> as he ſaid of himſelf? And what was <hi>Iſaac, Abrahams</hi> Son to the Lord Jeſus, God's Son? For he is ſimply, properly and abſolutely ſuch; which fundamental Truth to be confirmed in, I deſire the Reader to take the following Scripture Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences wherein he is ſo called, for I will omit no occaſion to aſſert it.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſort are immediately from Heaven; upon this account the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> before our Saviout was conceived, ſaid of him to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, <hi>he ſhall be called the Son of the Higheſt,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32. <hi>v.</hi> 35.</note> 
               <hi>and the Son of God.</hi> But at his Baptiſm in an Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick way, God the Father declared him ſuch from Heaven when this voice came thence,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art my beloved Son, in thee I am well pleaſed.</hi> It is ſpoken in the Second Perſon, which applies what we read of, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.17. where 'tis in the Third, <hi>This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> Confirmed in the Transfiguration, <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <p>Another kind of Evidences, thô from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were upon Earth, <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſaid of the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:172914:69"/>Jeſus,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.34. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.33.34. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and I ſaw and bare Record that this is the Son of God;</hi> this Teſtimony our Lord, thô he receives not teſtimony from man, as he ſaid, yet to condeſcend to the <hi>Jews</hi> unbelief, he appealed to, but chiefly to his Father's <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieſs</hi> words are another Evidence,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.49.</note> 
               <hi>Rabbi, thou art the Son of God, thou art the King of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> Obſerve how the Title King of Iſrael, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely taken is the ſame as God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> To this add <hi>Peter's</hi> Confeſſion in his Name, and of the other Apoſtles,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 6 69.</note> 
               <hi>We believe and</hi> (obſerve) <hi>are ſure, that thou art that Chriſt, the Son of the living God.</hi> Our bleſſed Saviour, whoſe right and prerogative is to bear Record of himſelf, as he told the <hi>Jews,</hi> for
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.14.</note> 
               <hi>he knew whence he came and whither he went;</hi> in ſeveral places, as <hi>John</hi> 8.42, and 10. <hi>I ſaid I am the Son of God. Martha</hi> ſaid,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.27.</note> 
               <hi>I believe that thou art the Chriſt, the Son of God.</hi> The end of St <hi>John</hi>'s writing his Goſpel is,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.31.</note>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37.</note> 
               <hi>that ye may believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God.</hi> Upon this Faith the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch was Baptized by <hi>Philip.</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.26.</note> 
               <hi>I believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God:</hi> And by this funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Truth <hi>Paul</hi> after his Converſion began to Preach the Goſpel,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 4.41.</note> 
               <hi>that he,</hi> Chriſt <hi>is the Son of God;</hi> other places I omit, theſe being ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to confirm this fundamental and eſſential Truth of the Goſpel, that Jeſus is the Son of God, in a true and proper Senſe.</p>
            <p>We might bring in a third ſort of Evidence, for not only Heaven and Earth, but Hell alſo hath owned that Truth; for
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 4.41.</note> 
               <hi>the Devils</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>cry'd out and ſaid, thou art Chriſt the Son of God.</hi> The very Heathens ſaid no leſs, for the Centurion and they that were with him, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jeſus at his death, ſaid,
<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.54.</note> 
               <hi>truly this was the Son of God:</hi> A Truth which no Chriſtian, no
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:172914:69"/>Child of God will deny, after ſo many clear Proofs.</p>
            <p>This ſhort digreſſion I have been put upon, after the peruſal of a moſt damnable <hi>Socinian</hi> Pamphlet, of two whole Sheets, which is fallen into my hands ſince this was under the Preſs, it hath two Titles, the firſt, <hi>A Dialogue by way of Queſtions and Anſwers concerning the Deity:</hi> The laſt, <hi>A brief, but clear Confutation of the Doctrine of the Trinity,</hi> ſtuffed with the quinteſſence of diabolical and moſt abominable Impieties and Blaſphemies uſual with that ſort of Men, with Texts of Scripture wreſted and miſapplied, with ſeveral impertinent Objections, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again have been
<note n="(a)" place="margin">See Gailhard againſt the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy.</note> anſwered and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded. That wicked Spirit is reſtleſs; neither Authority of Scripture, true Reaſon, nor Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> are able to quiet them, but they will vent their venom, ſpiritual ignorance, and the gall of bitterneſs which is in them, againſt the moſt Holy Trinity, and the Perſons of the Son and of the Holy Ghoſt. Fooliſh and crackt Men may be pitied, but when the humour turns into Rage and Fury, then mad Men ſhould be Chained up, to prevent their doing others miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. How often in this laſt part doth that helliſh Inſtrument prophane and take God's Name in vain, with ſaying <hi>good God,</hi> when he ſpits in his Face, and curſes him in his heart? But how much reaſon have we to cry out, good God, that ſuch horrid Blaſphemies which make Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians hair ſtand on end, ſhould come abroad, and the Author go unpuniſhed?</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>England,</hi> within thy Bowels thou haſt the two moſt curſed things that are or can be, and the moſt abominable to God, <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> wrapt up in <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> and <hi>Popery:</hi> The
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:172914:70"/>one denies the Lord that bought them, to be God as he is; the other, every day Crucifies him, and with attributing to the Creature, that which belongs only to the Creator, namely Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and to forgive Sins, hath matched and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centered Blaſphemy with Idolatry; that Society under the notion of <hi>probability,</hi> doth admit of any, thô never ſo abominable Doctrine, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of <hi>directing the Intention,</hi> receives all execrable practices; yet this is known, ſeen and ſuffered; but thô Men do, God will not. But as puniſhment is tied to the tail of Sin, God in his due time will make us ſmart for it: Are we thus reſcued from <hi>Popery,</hi> when by a deteſtable tolleration or winking at, againſt the Laws of God, of the Land, and the Rules of true Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, we are more than overgrown with it: I wiſh God doth not lay it to the charge of the Government; is it poſſible for <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to forget the cruel Canons of the Councils of <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> and of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and the Congregation in <hi>Rome,</hi> for the <hi>Propagation of their Faith, and the Extirpation of Hereticks,</hi> or can <hi>England</hi> forget bloody <hi>Mary</hi>'s Reign, the barbarous <hi>Iriſh</hi> Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facre, which is ſtill a bleeding, and what of late, <hi>James</hi> would have been at, to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the Northern Hereſie, as <hi>Colman</hi> in his Letters called the Proteſtant Religion: This is freſh in every ones memory; and there are upon Record the Injuſtice and Cruelties practiſed in <hi>Bohemia, Sileſia,</hi> and <hi>Hungary;</hi> what bloody perſecutions have formerly been, and now are acted in <hi>France,</hi> and in the <hi>Palatinate?</hi> Are we quite infatuated? Have we forfeited common Senſe and Reaſon, that we leave a back Door open for <hi>Rome,</hi> to pour in her Emiſſaries upon, and to blow the Fire of Diviſion among us?
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:172914:70"/>The Inland and Foreign Prieſts, who come o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with all freedom, ſay as many Maſſes, and may be more than are Sermons every day preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the City, and uſe all poſſible means to undermine our Holy Religion and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment too, thô it be not minded, which is a great Sin, and may happen to be ſoon followed with a heavy puniſhment: But I muſt return to my main deſign, which tends to perſwade Men to leave Sin and all, to gain Chriſt, to Love, Fear, Honour and Obey him.</p>
            <p>Out of theſe Conſiderations, let us all for God's ſake and our own good, in our ſeveral Stations, do ſomething for him, who hath done ſo much for us: Leave off, puniſh and diſcourage Sin. Chriſt died for us, therefore for his ſake,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Let us mortifie our Members which are upon Earth, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, inordinate Affection, evil Concupiſcence,</hi> &amp;c. He was Crucified for us; then let our old Man and his deeds be Crucified with him, never preferring to pleaſe one Member, one Senſe, one Paſſion before him, who is all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together lovely, ought to be the deſire of our Souls, as
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Haggai</hi> 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>He is the deſire of all Nations,</hi> and
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.1.</note> 
               <hi>mighty to ſave</hi> that Strong One, out of whom came forth Sweeneſs, called,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>the Lion of the Tribe of Judah,</hi> whom in the New Teſtament we read of is transformed into a Lamb, and ſo all along after repreſented by a Lamb, as it had been ſlain, of whom may well be ſaid what we read of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> one of his Types,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.30.</note> 
               <hi>the dead which he ſlew at his death, were more than they which he ſlew in his life.</hi> O that I could ſo indear this bleſſed Saviour to the Souls of Men as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the proud for his meekneſs ſake, to part with his Pride; with the unclean, for his holineſs ſake, with his uncleanneſs; and ſo with
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:172914:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:172914:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:172914:72"/>every ſinner elſe, to part with his Sins in al kinds, or elſe reſolve to loſe Chriſt for ever; for <hi>Chriſt hath no Concord with Belial;</hi> be not miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, God will be ſanctified either by, or on us all.</p>
            <p>The Song touching the Vineyard muſt be minded;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.</note> it was planted in a very fruitful Hill, fenced, the Stones gathered out of it, planted with the choiceſt Vine, a Tower built in the midſt of it, and nothing wanting that labour and induſtry could afford to improve it; yet after all this Care, inſtead of bringing forth Grapes, that ungrateful Vineyard brought forth wild Grapes: This is the literal Senſe of the Parable, but there the Prophet declares the moral Senſe of it; how the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is the Vineyard of the Lord of Hoſts, to whoſe Judgement he refers the Caſe, betwixt him and his Vineyard, ſo juſt and ſo plain it is againſt it, and thereby ſets before their Eyes their ingratitude and God's mercy. Now what the Apoſtle ſaith, in another Caſe, may well be appli'd to this,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>it was not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for his ſake alone, but for us alſo.</hi> Thus I may ſay, <hi>England,</hi> thou art the Vineyard, God hath planted thee in a pleaſant and plentiful Country, thou haſt enjoyed the light and warmth of the Sun, the former and the latter Rain, the upper and the nether Springs, and all Bleſſings from Heaven; yet how barren of late, and now more than ever, are we under thoſe means of Grace? inſtead of Grapes and Figs, bitter and ſowr Fruits; the Olive, Vine and Fig-trees are turned into Thorns, Bryars and Brambles: How plainly, abundantly and gloriouſly hath God's Word been Preached here, I dare ſay, more, at leaſt as much as in any other Country ſince the coming of Chriſt; but what fruits of Repentance, Faith,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:172914:72"/>Charity, Holineſs, and Juſtice have we brought forth? Now the generality is quite degenerated, and God hath as much cauſe to ſay to us, as he did to the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>I looked for Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but behold Oppreſſion, for Righteouſneſs, but behold a Cry:</hi> Moſt, if not all follow the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their evil Heart, we are over head and ears in Sin; and what the Apoſtle ſaith of
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>the whole World,</hi> we may ſay the moſt part of the Nation <hi>lyeth,</hi> and is ſuffered to lie <hi>in wickedneſs:</hi> This ſhould make us afraid of the Vineyards doom,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai,</hi> 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>I will tell you what I will do to my Vineyard, I will take away the Hedge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and it ſhall be eaten up, and break down the Wall thereof, and it ſhall be trodden down, and I will lay it waſte, it ſhall not be pruned, nor digged, but there ſhall come up Briars and Thorns; I will alſo command the Clouds that they Rain not upon it.</hi> That is, he will withdraw his Graces. The Navy is <hi>England</hi>'s Hedge and Wall, which of late hath been Tottering, and hath not appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that Glory, Vigour and Strength as it did formerly; whereby we lie more than ever open to an Enemy; and the fear and danger of it is upon many: So there are Dangers, Fears, and Judgments, and we ſhould remember the Flood, how, of ſo many Millions in the old World, only Eight Perſons eſcaped drowning; and of <hi>Sodom, Gomorrah,</hi> and the other wicked Towns, only <hi>Lot</hi> and his Two Daughters were ſaved from that ſignal Judgment. And if God was pleaſed after the War, to ſend Plague, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and other grievous Judgments upon us, beſides that of Sin, which we are overflown with, and we ſhould ſay,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>wherefore doth the Lord our God all theſe things unto us? Then ſhalt thou an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, like as ye have forſaken me, and ſerved ſtrange
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:172914:73"/>Gods in your Land, ſo ſhall ye ſerve ſtrangers in a Land that is not yours:</hi> As if he had ſaid, as you have done againſt me, ſo ſhall <hi>it</hi> be againſt you, and your puniſhment ſhall be of the ſame nature as your Sin hath been; wherein the Prophet fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells their Captivity; and have not many of us inſtead of God, ſerved the Idols of their ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, pleaſures and riches, and forſaken Piety, Virtue and true Honour? Are we not guilty of the like Sins as was the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which the Prophet mentions, with a
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>Woe unto them that riſe up early in the Morning that they may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſtrong Drink that continue until Night, till the Wine inflame them,</hi> and
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>that are mighty to drink Wine, and Men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong Drink:</hi> Is not this the Caſe here? is not drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs an Epidemical Sin, again,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>who call evil good, and good evil; that put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs; bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter; that are wiſe in their own Eyes, and prudent in their own ſight; which juſtifie the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Reward, and take away the righteouſneſs of the righteous from him.</hi> Doth not every thing here reach ſome of us? But in the ſame Chapter the Prophet adds, <hi>the Harp and the Viol, the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bret and Pipe, and Wine are in their Feaſts;</hi> but mark what follows, as a mighty aggravation, <hi>but they regard not the work of the Lord, neither conſider the operation of his hands;</hi> an effect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, <hi>therefore my People are gone into Captivity:</hi> But that which is worſe and damnable, <hi>therefore Hell hath enlarged her ſelf and opened her mouth without meaſure.</hi> If it were but the Grave, it were enough to terrifie Men from ſuch things, and in <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25.26. we read of further Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments very terrible, with a <hi>therefore,</hi> to ſhew they are the fruits of their Sins; which ſhould
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:172914:73"/>make us all fear and tremble. They are God's own Words to the ſame People, to us as well as to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>Fear ye not me ſaith the Lord, will ye not tremble at my Preſence?</hi> If ye do not, I will make you before I have done: For all theſe Judgments which ye feel, my anger is not turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, but my hand is ſtretched out ſtill.</p>
            <p>Not long before his death,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Joſhua</hi> gathered the People to put them in mind of what God had done for them, to repreſent unto them their Duty, and gave them a ſtrict charge about it, in a remarkable circumſtance,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 26.27.</note> 
               <hi>he took a great Stone and ſet it up there, and ſaid behold this Stone ſhall be a Witneſs unto us, for it hath heard all the words of the Lord.</hi> God uever wanteth Witneſſes, and rather than fail, the very Stones ſhall ſpeak: However, he often is pleaſed to make uſe of weak Inſtruments, whoſe Teſtimony is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected when they ſpeak in his Name, and out of his own Word: As for me who am come to an Age wherein I have little to hope for, deſire, or fear from Men, and tho' I had, I would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways. Fear God rather than Men; therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtructed by ſome experience, which my God hath given me of his gracious and wiſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, do now upon this nice and important con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, give in my Evidence for God, and a ſerious warning to all Sinners in the Land; I begin with, and ſpeak to my ſelf firſt, as the chief of Sinners, then to King, Parliaments, Judges, Magiſtrates, Clergymen, and others, of all Conditions, Ages, Relations and Profeſſions whatſoever, as at the laſt and terrible day we ſhall anſwer to God, every one within our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Stations, as much as in us lieth, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and promote Piety, and Virtue, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance, puniſh and ſuppreſs Error and Vice,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:172914:74"/>and let every one begin with himſelf in his own Perſon, or elſe, I denounce God's terrible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Judgments upon you and upon me, and theſe lines of mine ſhall upon occaſion, if we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect our Duty, be Evidences againſt you and againſt me; this is neither time nor thing to flatter, or to dally with, for
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 16.46.</note> 
               <hi>there is wrath gone out from the Lord, the plague is begun;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hear that faithful Servant of God, <hi>Moſes,</hi> as ſpeaking to you,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.35.</note> 
               <hi>ſee, I have this day ſet before thee, life and death, good and evil,</hi> light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Heaven and Hell, Chriſt and Sin, chuſe well, and be wiſe unto Salvation: I have brought and laid a looking Glaſs before all, wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one may ſee himſelf; therefore make a right uſe of it; as much as I could, I made what I ſaid to reach all: I hope none that is good will take ill what I write; as for the bad, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent, I neither intend nor care to pleaſe them, truth doth offend ſome, who thereupon hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en themſelves, others are better for hearing it, and mend? theſe will thank God for the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he affords them to learn by being told, to the other in <hi>Pauls</hi> words, I ſay,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>am I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore become your Enemy, becauſe I tell you the truth;</hi> but know, I will not betray it for any Man's ſake.</p>
            <p>Our Sins are many, great and frequent, and God's hand is lifred up againſt us, therefore let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, Prince and Subject, High and Low, Rich and Poor, Man and Woman, Young and Old, mend and repent, and in his place do his duty, or elſe,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>prepare to meet thy God O Iſrael,</hi> If not in the way of Repentance, in that of his Judgments, which I am afraid are hanging over our heads, at leaſt we have cauſe to think ſo; therefore hear ye the ſound of the Trumpet,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:172914:74"/>and know the meaning of it; learn and be wiſe, for thereby God doth invite us all to repent, and to mind his work and Service, which is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, Glorious and Profitable: But if blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trumpet in <hi>Sion</hi> cannot do with, but be neglected by Men, then
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord alſo ſhall roare out of Sion,</hi> nay, hath already roared, and if
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>the Lion hath roared, who will not fear?</hi> 'Tis a terrible voice which denounceth Judgments, and thundereth Threatnings, and if yet by this, Men will not be awaked from their Sins, then, at that
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel</hi> 2.31.</note> 
               <hi>great, and very terrible day of the Lord,</hi> at laſt they ſhall come out of their Graves, to ſuffer the puniſhment due to their impenitence and unbelief, when
<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord himſelf ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the voice of the Archangel, and with the Trumpet of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May the great God, our moſt gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be pleaſed to prevent us with Temporal bleſſings, to continue with Spiritual, and to end with Eternal, by the merits and mediation of his only begotten Son, our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, through the powerful working of the Holy Ghoſt, in one moſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and undivided Godhead, three Perſons, Co-eſſential in Nature, Co-eternal in Time, and Co-equal in Power, to whom be, by every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture rendred as moſt due, all Honour, Glory, Power, Majeſty and Dominion, now, and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:75"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>D. Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>FOur Tracts;</hi> 1. <hi>A ſhore Diſcourſe about</hi> Divorce <hi>and its Cauſes,</hi> Fornication <hi>and</hi> Adultery. 2. <hi>A Charge to Judges, Juries, and Witneſſes concerning</hi> Oaths. 3. <hi>About</hi> Infant <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> 4. <hi>A</hi> Letter <hi>to a Lady who hath forſaken the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Religion for the</hi> Romiſh, <hi>The</hi> 2. <hi>Edition</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Free Thoughts, in Defence of a Future State as diſcoverable by natural Reaſon, and ſtript of all Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious appendages. Demonſtrating againſt the nominal Deiſts, that the conſideration of Future Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages is a juſt motive to Virtue, of Future loſs and miſery, a powerful and becoming reſtraint of Vice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With occaſional Remarks on a Book Intituled, an enquiry concerning Virtue, and a Refutation of the revived Hylyzoiciſm of</hi> Democritus <hi>and</hi> Leucippus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A compleat Hiſtory or Survey of all the diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and methods of Religion from the beginning of the World to the conſummation of all things, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the Old and New Teſtament, ſhewing the ſeveral Reaſons and Deſigns of thoſe different Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, and the wiſdom and goodneſ of God in the Government of his Church, through all the Ages of it, in which alſo the Opinion of Dr.</hi> Spencer <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Rights and Sacrifices is examined, and the certainty of the Chriſtian Religion demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, the Cavils of the Deiſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>By</hi> John Edwards. <hi>C. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172914:75"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
